<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Archive of Digital Editions of Valentine and Orson</title>
                <sponsor>
                    <name> University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </funder>
                <editor>
                    <name>Anna Kroon</name>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Anna Kroon</persName>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>This edition was created for the University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship to digitally reproduce
                    various chapbook, picture book, and other editions of Valentine and Orson.</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Anna Kroon</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>300 Boston Post Rd</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>West Haven, CT 06516</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/legalcode">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2018-07-27">July 27, 2018 <!-- CHANGE THIS AS NEEDED!!!!!! --></date>
                <distributor>TEI Archiving, Publishing, and Access Service (TAPAS)</distributor>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Renowned Hisotry of Valentine and Orson: The Two Sons of the Emperor of Greece</title>
                    <pubPlace>Haverhill</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Peter Edes</publisher>
                    <date>MDCCXCIV</date>. </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>This project encodes various chapbook, picture book, and other versions of the medieval romance story, Valentine and Orson, using
                    the extensible markup language for detailed presentation of the text. The goal of the project is to create a digital archive of
                    available versions of this story with project specific encoding guidelines created in accordance with the Text Encoding Initiative
                    P5 Guidelines. The editions and project guidelines are available on the TEI Archiving, Publishing, and Access Service and GitHub
                    repositories. </p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Texts for this project were selected from the available collections at the Beinecke Rare Books Library, Rare Books and Special
                    Collections at McGill University and the Baldwin Library of Historical Children's Literature George A. Smathers Libraries at
                    University of Florida. </p>
            </samplingDecl>

            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Text is presented with no corrections or normalizations to spellings or printing errors. </p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p>Punctuation spacing has been normalized in cases where excessive spacing exists.</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p>Original quotation marks or lack thereof have been preserved. In all cases of spoken dialogue the “said” tag was used.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Hyphenation for line breaks and page breaks has not been retained. All other hyphenation and dash usage has been retained. </p>
                </hyphenation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p>Texts are presented with limited interpretive mark up. Only the main body of the story has been encoded. Images for pages not
                        encoded are provided. See descriptive outline below. </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <pb n="i" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/856/42771403535_3f3e4ba492_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="ii" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/862/43674297461_e95a07bff3_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/938/42771403675_9f33169f94_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="iv" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/937/43674297731_304d550348_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="v" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/930/42771403855_b6b47a5e48_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="vi" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/925/43674297861_49ca169278_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/862/42771403985_01c6c3841d_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE <lb/>RENOWNED <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON,</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="sub">THE TWO SONS <lb/>OF THE <lb/>EMPEROR OF GREECE.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>HAVERHILL,</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>PRINTED BY <name>PETER EDES.</name></publisher>
                    <docDate>MDCCXCIV.</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="2" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1830/42275779635_8da8049c21_o_d.jpg"
                resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="book">
                <pb n="3" facs="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/921/42275780015_62056f02d2_o_d.jpg"
                    resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
                <head>The <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON.</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                    <ab>How King Pepin baniſhed his Queen Bertha, and how he gave his ſiſter Belliſant, in marriage to Alexander, emperor of
                        Conſtantinople.</ab>
                    <p>WE find it ſet down in ancient Chronicale, that the thrice noble and valiant Pepin, king of France, took to wife Bertha, who
                        was deſended of royal race. This lady was very fair and wiſe, but much incumbered with troubles, which with great patience ſhe
                        ſuffered. The chief inſtrument of all the miſchief towards this good queen, was plotted by a falſe old woman who firſt brought
                        her in <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">diſgrace</fw>
                        <pb n="4" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1770/42275780265_395928f2dd_o_d.jpg"
                            resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">4 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>diſgrace with the king her huſband, and after to be baniſhed his bed,
                        while ſhe in a cunning manner brought in her daughter in the queen's ſtead. This old woman having brought her treachery to
                        effect, for (her daughter was very like Bertha) it forcame to paſs, that king Pepin had two ſons by this maiden, viz. Haufrey
                        and Henry, both which ſons ſo grieved the king, and waſted the country of France by thier outrages and fury, that they cauſed
                        the queen to be utterly baniſhed; by which ſhe endured many ſorrowful days; but at laſt ſhe began to recieve confort again,
                        for ſo it happened, that at the requeſt of divers lords of France, this good queen began to fing favor with the king her
                        huſband, who when he knew the treachery of that wicked woman againſt her, he much bewailed the miſery ſhe had endured, and
                        recieved her again with great honor and triumph. The queen reſtored to her former bed, conceived and bore the king a ſon,
                        called Charlemain the Puiſſant.</p>
                    <p>This king Pepin had a ſiſter named Belliſant, a woman of great wit and beauty. It chanced ſo that the fam of this lovely
                        perſonage ſpread abroad, that at laſt Alexander, emperor of Conſtantinople, came <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >into</fw><pb n="5" facs="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1787/42275780595_b1db767cca_o_d.jpg"
                            resp="Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON.
                            5</fw><lb/> into France, accompanied with a gallant troop of his nobility. This emperor after his arrival, ſuddenly
                        aſſembled all his lords, in their rich habiliments, appointing them to take their way towards king Pepin's court. King Pepin
                        underſtanding this ſudeen but joygul news, made great preparations for entertaining this emperor. King Pepin, with all his
                        noble train, went to meet the emperor, with great joy, and conducted him to the court of France, where fair Belliſant was, and
                        ſhe entertained him with no leſs joy than her brother had done before.</p>
                    <p>This marriage being known among all the inhabitants, there was great joy on every ſide. When the time appointed came, theſe two
                        were eſpouſed in all honor fitting for their eſtates. This marriage feaſt held long, btu being ended, the emperor preprared to
                        take his leave of his new brother-in-law, and take his way towards Conſtantinople, with his fiar empreſs Beliſant. Theſe
                        mighty princes name near a port of the ſea, where they were obliged to take leave of each other, which they done with ſuch
                        tenderneſs, as I am not able to ecpreſs, giving his ſiſter many rich gifts, and then embraced her, with <lb/><fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">A2</fw><lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">weeping</fw></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
