<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Archive of Digital Editions of Valentine and Orson</title>
            <sponsor>
               <name> University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
            </sponsor>
            <funder>
               <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
            </funder>
            <editor>
               <name>Anna Kroon</name>
            </editor>
            <principal>
               <persName>Anna Kroon</persName>
            </principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This edition was created for the University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship to digitally reproduce
               various chapbook, picture book, and other editions of Valentine and Orson.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Anna Kroon</publisher>
            <address>
               <addrLine>300 Boston Post Rd</addrLine>
               <addrLine>West Haven, CT 06516</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/legalcode">Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International</licence>
            </availability>
            <date when="2018-07-26">July 26, 2018</date>
            <distributor>TEI Archiving, Publishing, and Access Service (TAPAS)</distributor>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>The Marquis of Carabas' Picture Book</title>
               <author>Walter Crane</author>
               <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
               <publisher>George Routledge and Sons</publisher></bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This project encodes various chapbook, picture book, and other versions of the medieval romance story, Valentine and Orson, using
               the extensible markup language for detailed presentation of the text. The goal of the project is to create a digital archive of
               available versions of this story with project specific encoding guidelines created in accordance with the Text Encoding Initiative
               P5 Guidelines. The editions and project guidelines are available on the TEI Archiving, Publishing, and Access Service and GitHub
               repositories. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>Texts for this project were selected from the available collections at the Beinecke Rare Books Library, Rare Books and Special
               Collections at McGill University and the Baldwin Library of Historical Children's Literature George A. Smathers Libraries at
               University of Florida. </p>
         </samplingDecl>
         
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction>
               <p>Text is presented with no corrections or normalizations to spellings or printing errors. </p>
            </correction>
            <normalization>
               <p>Punctuation spacing has been normalized in cases where excessive spacing exists.</p>
            </normalization>
            <quotation>
               <p>Original quotation marks or lack thereof have been preserved. In all cases of spoken dialogue the “said” tag was used.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Hyphenation for line breaks and page breaks has not been retained. All other hyphenation and dash usage has been retained. </p>
            </hyphenation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Texts are presented with limited interpretive mark up. Only the main body of the story has been encoded. Images for pages not
                  encoded are provided. See descriptive outline below. </p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>This research project was conceived as a research proposal for the University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship. For
            this project I thought I was going to be delving into morals, lessons, and themes in historical children’s literature to see if I could
            understand the values of society through what adults teach to children. To do this I was going to create digital editions of various
            children’s books from a, at the time unspecified, year in the 19th century. Then I stumbled on a beautifully illustrated picture book by
            Mr. Walter Crane (included in this collection). The Marquis of Carabas’s Picture book includes the stories of Puss in Boots, Old Mother
            Hubbard, Valentine and Orson, and the Absurd ABCs. The first two stories I had heard of, and of course I know my ABCs, but I had never
            read Valentine and Orson. This caught my attention, so I looked for more. And so many more I found.</p>

         <p>When I began my research into children’s literature Valentine and Orson was not a story I was expecting to find. Twin brothers separated
            at birth who then reunite to fight injustice was not even close to my imagined ‘historical children’s literature’. My expectations aligned
            more with something like the Three Little Kittens that is more domestically and morally focused. I began by reading scholarship about
            children’s literature and its history. Through this research I learned a great deal about the development of a distinct genre for children
            and the shift from religious drama to light-hearted fantasy. After research I took a cursory look into digitized library archives to find
            potential artifacts and examples of the form. During this part of my research I found the picture book that changed my collection.</p>

         <p>This collection is comprised of 5 different versions of Valentine and Orson. These were selected as a sort of survey of the different
            styles and centuries’ treatment of the story. The process of selection was partly based on versions I thought were interesting and partly
            which copies were in legible and permitted for use. Ideally I would have included a larger range of publication dates and formats, but
            there were restrictions on my time, ability, and availability of the texts. The biggest constraint on the entire process was my time and
            transcription speed. There are many copies of chapbooks that I have not included as their content is very similar to the Jewitt and R. P.
            &amp;C. Williams chapbooks included in the collection and I wanted to ensure a variety of story adaptations. There are some longer
            versions, such as the Edes version used in the encoding guidelines, with much more complicated storylines that took so long to encode they
            were not able to be included in this particular collection. Still others were in poor condition, in foreign libraries, or still under
            copyright.</p>

         <p>To create these digital editions I transcribed and encoded each text with the eXtensible Markup Language following the Text Encoding
            Initiative P5 Guidelines. Throughout this process I had to make decisions about what would be represented and how it would be represented
            to create a set of project specific guidelines (the record in this collection entitled Encoding Guide, view in XML mode to see the
            markup). Then I checked each for mistakes by having the text read out character by character and comparing that to the transcription.
            Finally I linked each edition’s images to the page beginnings and figure markers and uploaded them onto the TAPAS platform. Please see the
            individual editions’ TEI header for information on editorial decisions.</p>
         <p>I am continuing my work in my thesis research. I am working on representing adaptation and story variation through encoding. Once that
            project is complete all artifacts in this collection will be revised to include the new encoding.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
