<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Marquis of Carabas' Picture Book</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">The MARQUIS of<lb/>CARABAS his</titlePart>
               <figure/>
               <titlePart type="main">PICTURE<lb/>BOOK</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
         </titlePage>
         <!-- THERE ARE A COUPLE OF LEFT OUT PAGES HERE -->
         <pb n="5"/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE<lb/>MARQUIS OF CARABAS'<lb/>PICTURE BOOK</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="desc">CONTAINING<lb/>PUSS IN BOOTS<lb/>OLD MOTHER HUBBARD<lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON<lb/>THE ABSURD A B
                  C<lb/>WITH<lb/>THIRTY-TWO PAGES OF ILLUSTRATIONS BY WALTER CRANE.<lb/>PRINTED IN COLOURS BY EDMUND EVANS.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint>
               <pubPlace>LONDON</pubPlace>
               <publisher>GEORGE ROUTLEDGE AND SONS</publisher>
               <pubPlace>THE BROADWAY, LUDGATE<lb/>NEW YORK: 416 BROOME STREET</pubPlace>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <!-- Many pages not included -->
      <body>
         <div type="story">
            <pb n="40"/>
            <ab>ONCE on a time an Emperor, a man of might and fame,<lb/>Married a wife, and fair was she, and Bellisant her name;<lb/>And fair and
               happy were their lives, until an evil man<lb/>(he was the High Priest of the Court) an evil tale began,<lb/>Of how the lady was not
               true unto her husband dear:<lb/>The Emperor believed the tale, and rose up in great fear,<lb/>And drove poor Bellisant away; in haste
               and dire mischance<lb/>She took her way to Pepin's Court (her brother, King of France)</ab>
            <figure/>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">1</fw>
            <pb n="41"/>
            <figure/>
            <ab>And as she fled, weighed down by grief and sense of cruel scorn,<lb/>Lo, in the forest two fair sons to Bellisant were born;<lb/>But
               while her servant went to buy some food, a great she-bear<lb/><lb/>Poor Bellisant ran after her, with many a sigh and moan;<lb/>In
               vain,—and when she turned again, the other child was gone!</ab>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">2</fw>
            <pb n="42"/>
            <pb n="43"/>
            <pb n="44"/>
            <figure/>
            <ab>Now, Pepin chanced that very day to hunt with all his train<lb/>In that same wood, and found the child ere she came back
               again;<lb/>And took him home, and brought him up, and gave him all thing fine—<lb/>Apparel, horses, and a name,—so he was
               VALENTINE.<lb/>And brave and fair he grew,—King Pepin's daughter loved him well;<lb/>The sons were jealous. Now will I his brother's
               story tell.</ab>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">3</fw>
            <pb n="45"/>
            <pb n="46"/>
            <!-- start weird two pages -->
            <ab>The she-bear and her savage cubs, they saved the child alive,<lb/>And nursed him well, and tended him,—well did he grow and
               thrive,<lb/>They called him ORSON; in the woods he lived, a strong wild man,<lb/>And all he fought he killed with ease; and so a wicked
               plan<lb/>Was made by Pepin's sons for getting rid of Valentine,<lb/>Whom they induced to fight wih him, by flattering words and
               fine.<lb/>But Valentine was conqueror, and Orson owned his might,<lb/>And served and followed him alway: and they were squire and
               knight.</ab>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="47"/>
            <!-- end of weird two pages -->
            <pb n="48"/>
            <pb n="49"/>
            <figure/>
            <ab>Now, in that land there dwelt a man, the Green Knight he was called,<lb/>Who by his strength and magic arts a lady fair
               enthralled,<lb/>And kept in a prison dark and strong, and none could set her free;<lb/>Not even Valentine prevailed, with all his
               bravery.</ab>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">6</fw>
            <pb n="50"/>
            <pb n="51"/>
            <pb n="52"/>
            <ab>But Orson threw the Green Knight down, and bound him with a chain,<lb/>And set the lady free; both brothers then start off to
               gain<lb/>The Green Knight's castle-gates,—two roaring lions kept guard there,<lb/>But down they crouched when they beheld the brothers
               void of fear.</ab>
            <figure/>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">7</fw>
            <pb n="53"/>
            <figure/>
            <ab>And there within the castle hall they saw a head of brass,<lb/>That uttered marvels,—of their birth, and how it came to pass;<lb/>How
               in a convent lonely was their mother Bellisant;<lb/>How the King and Queen of France were their uncle and their aunt;<lb/>How the High
               Priest had confessed his lies, with many tears and groans;<lb/>How the Emperor, their father, was in search of wife and sons.<lb/>So
               the lost were found, the wrong made right, by all good rule and line;<lb/>They married well, and lived long years—ORSON and
               VALENTINE.</ab>
            <fw type="footer" place="bottom">8</fw>
         </div>
         <!-- There are more pages here.  -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
