<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Marquis of Carabas' Picture Book</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <front>
        <!-- Should the cover go here and the title page? -->
     </front>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <ab>ONCE on a time an Emperor, a man of might and fame,
         <lb/>Married a wide, and fair was she, and Bellisant her name;
         <lb/>And fair and happy were their lives, until an evil man (he was the High Priest of the COurt) an evil tale began,
         <lb/>Of how the lady was not true unto her husband dear:
         <lb/>The Emperor believed the tale, and rose up in great fear,
         <lb/>And drove poor Bellisant away; in haste and dire mischance
         <lb/>She took her way to Pepin's Court (her brother, King of France)</ab>
         <figure></figure>
         <!-- There is a 1 at the bottom -->
         <pb/>
         <figure></figure>
         <ab>And as she fled, weighed down by grief and a sense of cruel scorn,
         <lb/>Lo, in the forest two fair sons to Bellisant were born;
         <lb/>But while her servant went to buy some food, a great she-bear
         <lb/>Came up, and carried off one child unto her distant lair.
         <lb/>Poor Bellisant ran after her, with many a sigh and moan;
         <lb/>In vain,—and when she turned again, the other child was gone!</ab>
         <!-- Number 2 -->
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure></figure>
         <ab>now, Pepin chanced that very day to hunt with all his train
         <lb/>In that same wood, and found the child ere she came back again;
         <lb/>And took him home, and brought him up, and gave him all thing fine—
         <lb/>Apparel, horses, and a name,— so he was VALENTINE.
         <lb/>And brave and fair he grew,—King Pepin's daughter loved him well;
         <lb/>The sons were jealous. Now will I his brother's story tell.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <!-- HOW DO I ENCODE THESE PAGES THE TEXT GOES RIGHT ACROSS THE MIDDLE?!?! -->
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure></figure>
         <ab>Now, in that land there dwelt a man, the Green Knight he was called,
         <lb/>Who by his strength and magic arts a lady fair enthralled,
         <lb/>And kept in a prison dark and strong, and non could set her free;
         <lb/>Not even Valentine prevailed, with all his bravery.</ab>
         <pb/><pb/>
         <pb/>
         <ab>But Orson threw the Green Knight sown, and bound him with a chain,
         <lb/>And set the lady free; both brothers then start off to gain
         <lb/>The Green Knight's castle-gates,—two roaring lions kept guard there,
         <lb/>But down they crouched when they beheld the brothers void of fear.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure></figure>
         <ab>And there within the castle hall they saw a head of brass,
         <lb/>That uttered marvels,—of their birth and how it came to pass;
         <lb/>How in a convent lonely was their mother Bellisant;
         <lb/>How the King and Queen of France were thri uncle and thier aunt;
         <lb/>How the High Priest had confessed his les, with many tears and groans;
         <lb/>How the Emperor, their father, was in search of wife and sons,
         <lb/>So the lost were found, the wrong made right, by all good rule and line;
         <lb/>They married weel, and lived long years—ORSON and VALENTINE.</ab>
         
         <!-- There are more pages here.  -->
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
