<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Archive of Digital Editions of Valentine and Orson</title>
                <sponsor>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </funder>
                <editor>
                    <name>Anna Kroon</name>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Anna Kroon</persName>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- editionStmt is optional, but recommended by TEI-C guidelines if in case of multiple editions. It is used to group information on a single edition of text -->
                <edition>Edition statement...</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <!-- publicationStmt is mandatory. It groups information concerning the publication or distribution of the digital TEI object; use <sourceDesc> section below to record publication data that may be different than TEI edition, say for an historical source work.  -->
                <publisher><!-- the person or ogranization responsible for the creation of TEI edition, and who has rights over its production and/or distribution -->Publisher
                    Name</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><!-- repeat addrLine as needed -->Address Line 1,</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <!-- availability statement clarifies a general copyright and fair use policy governing reuse of the TEI edition -->
                    <licence target="URL_of_full_license"> Summary statement of which license applies to this TEI file </licence>
                    <p><!-- okay to add <p> to include other related but necessary blocks of information -->Availablity statement continued...</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2017-01-01"><!-- the date of publication of the TEI edition -->Publication Date</date>
                <distributor><!-- you can identify organization responsible for the distribution or purchase handling of the TEI edition -->Distributor
                    of this TEI Edition</distributor>
                <date><!-- provide a date for update on availability statement if different than publication date -->Availability Date</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--  <seriesStmt>
                seriesStmt is optional. It records the relation between separate documents understood as each part of a series (e.g., collected works (essays, lectures, articles, etc.), document volumes, etc.) by declaring its parent work/identity 
                <title level="s">Title of Series</title>
                <respStmt>
                    name of person responsible for series, e.g., editor or organization 
                    <resp>ed. by...</resp>
                    <name>Name of Editor</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope unit="vol">biblScope...</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">idno...</idno>
            </seriesStmt> -->

            <notesStmt>
                <!-- notesStmt is optional. It adds multiple notes for additional information or discussion of document -->
                <note><!-- repeat <note> as needed -->Notes on the text...</note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc is mandatory. It describes the source from which an electronic text was derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description <bibl> in the case of a digitized edition of a print text; in the case where the TEI file is born digital,we can include <p>"born digital"</p> -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>The renowned history of Valentine and Orson, the two sons of the Emperor of Greece</title>
                    <pubPlace>Haverhill</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Peter Edes</publisher>
                    <date>1794</date></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- encodingDesc section is optional, but recommended. It groups elements for recording information on the encoding practices used in relation to source work's orginal formatting; this section can range from a brief statement on encoding approach under <projectDesc> to a more detailed overview of editorial decisions under <editorialDesc> -->
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- a statment on purpose of TEI edition, project objectives, teams, etc -->
                <p>A Project Description ...</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <!-- can use this section to provide details on how text(s) at project level were selected -->
                <p> Information about text(s) in collection </p>
            </samplingDecl>

            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <!-- one might wish to note any "corrections" or alterations -->
                    <p>A Correction statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <!-- we can also record any regularization decisions made to source work in translating into a digital format -->
                    <p>A Normalization statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition for reasons of regularizing the work for digital
                        format</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p> Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation marks, etc.) </p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>This edition only retains hyphenation between words that would exist regardless of line breaks. Line break or page break
                        hyphenation has not be retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p> Information about any interpretive information added to the text </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- Inside cover has writing on it. To encode or not to encode? -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- more handwriting -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- empty page -->
            <pb/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE <lb/>RENOWNED <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON,</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="sub">THE TWO SONS <lb/>OF THE <lb/>EMPEROR OF GREECE.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>HAVERHILL,</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>PRINTED BY <name>PETER EDES.</name></publisher>
                    <docDate>MDCCXCIV.</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="book">
                <head>The <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON.</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                    <ab>How King Pepin baniſhed his Queen Bertha, and how he gave his ſiſter Belliſant, in marriage to Alexander, emperor of
                        Conſtantinople.</ab>
                    <p>WE find it ſet down in ancient Chronicale, that the thrice noble and valiant Pepin, king of France, took to wife Bertha, who
                        was deſended of royal race. This lady was very fair and wiſe, but much incumbered with troubles, which with great patience ſhe
                        ſuffered. The chief inſtrument of all the miſchief towards this good queen, was plotted by a falſe old woman who firſt brought
                        her in <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">diſgrace</fw>
                        <pb n="4"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">4 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/> diſgrace with the king her huſband, and after to be baniſhed his bed,
                        while ſhe in a cunning manner brought in her daughter in the queen's ſtead. This old woman having brought her treachery to
                        effect, for (her daughter was very like Bertha) it forcame to paſs, that king Pepin had two ſons by this maiden, viz. Haufrey
                        and Henry, both which ſons ſo grieved the king, and waſted the country of France by thier outrages and fury, that they cauſed
                        the queen to be utterly baniſhed; by which ſhe endured many ſorrowful days; but at laſt ſhe began to recieve confort again,
                        for ſo it happened, that at the requeſt of divers lords of France, this good queen began to fing favor with the king her
                        huſband, who when he knew the treachery of that wicked woman againſt her, he much bewailed the miſery ſhe had endured, and
                        recieved her again with great honor and triumph. The queen reſtored to her former bed, conceived and bore the king a ſon,
                        called Charlemain the Puiſſant.</p>
                    <p>This king Pepin had a ſiſter named Belliſant, a woman of great wit and beauty. It chanced ſo that the fam of this lovely
                        perſonage ſpread abroad, that at laſt Alexander, emperor of Conſtantinople, came <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >into</fw><pb n="5"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 5</fw><lb/> into France, accompanied with a
                        gallant troop of his nobility. This emperor after his arrival, ſuddenly aſſembled all his lords, in their rich habiliments,
                        appointing them to take their way towards king Pepin's court. King Pepin underſtanding this ſudeen but joygul news, made great
                        preparations for entertaining this emperor. King Pepin, with all his noble train, went to meet the emperor, with great joy,
                        and conducted him to the court of France, where fair Belliſant was, and ſhe entertained him with no leſs joy than her brother
                        had done before.</p>
                    <p>This marriage being known among all the inhabitants, there was great joy on every ſide. When the time appointed came, theſe two
                        were eſpouſed in all honor fitting for their eſtates. This marriage feaſt held long, btu being ended, the emperor preprared to
                        take his leave of his new brother-in-law, and take his way towards Conſtantinople, with his fiar empreſs Beliſant. Theſe
                        mighty princes name near a port of the ſea, where they were obliged to take leave of each other, which they done with ſuch
                        tenderneſs, as I am not able to ecpreſs, giving his ſiſter many rich gifts, and then embraced her, with <lb/><fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">A2</fw><lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">weeping</fw><pb n="6"/><fw type="header" place="top">6 THE
                            HISTORY OF</fw><lb/> weeping eyes he left her to the mercy of the waves. Then all the lords and ladies took their leave of
                        each other. The emperor and all his train arrived ſafe at Conſtantinople; at their landing, they were all recieved with great
                        joy and triumph. But mark what happened to the poor lady Belliſant, who by treaſon and falſe accuſations, was caſt out and
                        baniſhed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                    <ab>How the arch prieſt of Conſtantinople betrayed the emperor, by making love to fiar Belliſant the empreſs; and how the arch
                        prieſt, recieving a repulſe from Belliſant, practiſed treaſon againſt her.</ab>
                    <p>IN Conſtantinople lived and arch prieſt, in whom the emperor put great truſt, and committed to hom all his boſom ſecrets, and
                        made him governor over all his houſe; as alſo he was principal confeſſor, and one of his greateſt gavorites. The prieſt,
                        forgetting all the emperor's favors, and being overcome with the beauty<fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw><pb n="7"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 7</fw> of the new empreſs, inordinate luſt ſo far prevailed with him, that
                        one time ſpying her alone ſitting ſolitary in her chamber, he went in and ſat down by her. At firſt he began to behold her
                        with a ſmiling countenance, of all which the lady miſtruſted nothing, neither had ſhe any evil thought of him. But at laſt,
                        after many jeſtures of impurity, he begain to utter his laſcivious thoughts in a preſſing and amorous manner.</p>
                    <p>His ſpeeches being ended, the lady, out of a grave and prudent carriage, made an excellent anſwer to this wicked preiſt.—
                            <said>Thou falſe, unjuſt, and deviliſh prieſt! ſtain to thy profeſſion! how dareſt thou open thy mouth to ſuch a maſs of
                            cillanies as many thereon enſue? Firſt, as I may ſay, againſt the ſacred order; and ſecondly againſt the majeſty of that
                            emperor that ever nouriſhed thee, and hath raiſed thee to great ginities, and from whom may juſtly proceed the ſentence of
                            condemnation, both on thee and me, if he but knew thy laſacivious and wicked practices? Let gall, I ſay theſe vile
                            provocations to luſt, and leave for ever hereafter to ſolicit me in this manner; which if thou proſecuteſt any further,
                            thou canſt ex<fw type="catch" place="bottom">pect</fw><pb n="8"/><fw type="header" place="top">8 THE HISTORY OF</fw>pect
                            nothing but a ſhamefil downfall, and a moſt damnable death. Therefore depart, and ſee that you tempt me no
                        more.</said></p>
                    <p>This angry farewel of the worthy empreſs, ſtung the prieſt to the very heart, but he durſt make no reply, but craved pardon for
                        his bold and raſh follies comitted. This being ſore troubled in mind, he reſolved ſeveral days what to do againſt this
                        innocent lady.And feeling the emperor knew nothing of this matter from the empreſs, Belliſant, how the arch prieſt would have
                        enticed her to diſlotalty to him, but could not; therefore he began to accuſe her to the emperor for divers crimes. The arch
                        prieſt having now began to ſet abroach his deviliſh practices, he at laſt resolved that he would, under the cloak of
                        diſſimulation, make known his watchful care of his eſtate, welfare, and perſon. It fell out on a day when he ſpied the emperor
                        alone, he began to break out in this manner:</p>
                    <p><said>O emperor! thus it is, Belliſant, your wife, and ſiſter to the king of France, ſhe whom you advanced to this ſtate of
                            dignity, failed in the duty and loyalty which ſhe owes to her dread lord; for ſhe wandereth in her love, giving that to
                                another<fw type="catch" place="bottom">which</fw><pb n="9"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON 9</fw>
                            which is proper only to yourſelf. To name the perſon to your majeſty, I will not, for you know I am a ſacred prieſt, and
                            may not ſpill the blood of any man; but know for certain, that by the way of confeſſion I came to the light thereof,
                            whereof I neither ought nor will betray the name of him that thus betrays your bed; and what is worſe, ſhe daily deſires
                            your death, which grieves my heart to think on.</said></p>
                    <p>The emperor having heard this accuſation, little miſtrusſted the treachery of this arch prieſt, and gave credit to all his fair
                        but falſe words, and therewith became extreme penſive, that his truſt in her beauteous love had been thud decieved.</p>
                    <p>Upon a day entering into the chamber of his fair Brlliſant, without ſpeaking to her at all, in a fierce manner, her took her by
                        the hair of the head and dragged her about the chamber in a moſt inhuman manner, ſo the blood beſmeared her face. <said>Alas,
                            my lord,</said> ſad ſhe, <said>what moves you to this great outrage? I call the Gods to witneſs I never did any thing in
                            my life againſt your honor, or ever proſtituted my body to any ſtranger's love.</said> The emperor not being thus
                        ſatisfied, ſaid <said>thou<fw type="catch" place="bottom">whore!</fw><pb n="10"/><fw type="header" place="top">10 THE HISTORY
                                OF</fw> whore! I am too well informed of thy proceedings; and curſed be the day that I ſaw thy falſe, deceitful
                            face;</said> and with that daſhed her head againſt the ground, inſomuch, that all the damſels, her attendants, thought ſhe
                        had been dead.</p>
                    <p>The court being in an uproar upon this, up roſe a juſt, wiſe, courageous, and bold barron, and ſpoke to the emperor in this
                        manner: <said>Right worrthy ſir, I could wiſh you to be well adviſed; this lady id your eſpouſed wife, ſiſter to the great
                            king Pepin of France, whom when he ſhall hear of the great injury done to her, will muſter up all his men of war, and
                            ſuddenly ſurpriſe all our towns, wives, and children, and revenge upon us theſe cruel deeds unto his ſiſter.</said> The
                        worthy baron having thus ended his advice, the lady fell upon her knees before the emperor, and in tears thus ſhe ſpake.
                            <said>Alas, my lord, take pity on an innocent lady, for I am ſo free from any evil againſt your perſon or dignity. A
                            leaſt, my lord, poty the fruit of my body, for I am great with child by you. If nothing can appeaſe your anger to me, then
                            let my body be impriſoned in ſome ſtrong tower, until the time of my delive<fw type="catch" place="bottom">ry,</fw><pb
                                n="11"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 11</fw>ry, and then do with my body what pleaſeth you; ſo
                            the fruit of my body be kept ſafe.</said> The courtiers percieving nothing could mitigate the rage of the emperor, by a
                        common conſent removed her out of his preſence into another chamber. Having thus conveyed her away, the ladies that were her
                        attendants, fetched water to waſh her face, and did all they could to comfort her.</p>
                    <p>By this time the emperor's choler was a little pacified, by means of his lords and barons that attended him; inſomuch that he
                        cauſed Belliſant to be brought before him. When ſhe was come, his heart trembled and fretted for anger that he durſt not put
                        her to death, for fear of her mighty and puiſſant brother, king Pepin. <said>Thou curſed woman,</said> ſaid he, <said>were it
                            not for thy brother's ſake, the valiant Pepin of France, I would make thee fry in the fire as an example to all falſe
                            ladies.— Hear thy judgement. Now I baniſh thee out of my empire, and command that tomorrow thou depart out of this
                            city.</said></p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="12"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">12 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                    <ab>How the traitorous arch prieſt put on the habit of a kinght at arms, and being well mounted, followed the empreſs Belliſant,
                        who was lately baniſhed. How Belliſant in her baniſhment was delivered of two ſons in the wood, whoſe names were Valentine and
                        Orſon; and how ſhe loſt them.</ab>
                    <p>THE arch prieſt, having wrought the baniſhment of fair Belliſant, began to think how he ſhould ſurely accompliſh his deſire,
                        wherefore he changed his white rocket into a coat of ſteel and a ſword: and being thus accoutred, he mounted a milk-white
                        ſteed, and made after her with greateſt expedition, enquiring of all he met which way the lady Belliſant was gone. After ſome
                        hours riding he came to a ſpaious foreſt, taking the direct way towards the lady. It chanced as he caſt his eye aſide, he
                        ſpied the lady ith her ſervant, Blandiman, ſitting by a fountain, lamenting her miſerable fortune; Blandiman uſing all the
                        means he could to comfort her.—The falſe prieſt ſoon percieved it to be the lady; but, by reaſon of his <fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">diſguiſe,</fw><pb n="13"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 13</fw>diſguiſe, ſhe could not
                        imagine him to be the arch prieſt, her enemy, but coming nearer, ſhe quickly knew him, and being ſtruck with ſudden fear, ſaid
                        to her ſervant, <said>alas! I well percieve this to be the arch prieſt, coming toward us, and I am fearful left he comes to do
                            me farther villainy.</said>
                        <said>Lday,</said> ſaid Blandiman, <said>if her comes to do you further harm, I'll encounter him body for body.</said> The
                        arch prieſt was ready to alight from his horſe, to ſalute the lady; and after he had made himdſelf known to her, he ſaid to
                        her in this manner:</p>
                    <p><said>Dear lady, the caſe is ſo pitiful, as to ſuffer baniſhment by ſentence even againſt thee by the emperor; if thou wilth
                            give me entertainment in thy love, I will bring to paſd, that the emperor ſhall recal thy baniſhment, and make thee ſhine
                            more bright than before.</said>
                        <said>Ah!</said> quoth the lady, <said>thou diſloyal and traitorous adverſary, I have no cause to beſtow love where my life
                            hath been put in jeopardy.</said> Quoth he, <said>utter not ſuch expreſſions againſt me, for I am not come to vex or
                            trouble you.</said> And in ſpeaking theſe words, he bent his body to the lady, thinking to have kiſſed her, but Blandiman
                        perceiving his intent, got between them, and gave the arch prieſt <fw type="sig" place="bottom">B</fw><fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">ſuch</fw><pb n="14"/><fw type="header" place="top">14 THE HISTORY OF </fw>ſuch s ſtroke as felled him to
                        the earth. The arch priest has no ſooner recovered himſelf, but preſently ſiezed his ſword, which Blandiman perceiving, took a
                        glabe which he had about him; whereupon grew a fore fight between them: This encounter laſted ſo long that they were both
                        wounded; but at laſt a merchant came by, who percieving that fierce encounter, cried out, <said>lords, leave off, and tell me
                            the cauſe of your variance, and I'll endeavor to end this controverſy.</said>
                        <said>Sir,</said> quoth Blandiman, <said>let us firſt try our right by weapons, and then we will be ruled by words.</said> But
                        the poor lady could no longer bear ſilence, but ſaid to the merchant, <said>alas! this man which you ſee armed, is the falſe
                            and traitorous arch prieſt that hath followed me to rob me of my honor, and force me to inſatiable luſt; alſo this is he
                            that hath made a ſeparation between me and the emperor, my lord and huſband.</said></p>
                    <p>The merchant hearing her lamentable tale, ſaid to the arch prieſt, <said>ſir, prieſt, leave off your enterpriſe, dare not ſo
                            much as touch this innocent lady; for if the emperor underſtood this villainy, he would ſoon end they life of
                            infamy.</said> As ſoon as <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw><pb n="15"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND
                            ORSON. 15</fw>the arch prieſt heard this, he forſook his company and feld through the wood.—— But his villanies were
                        afterwards diſcloſed. The merchant ſtaid ſome little time, bewailing the hard hap of the lady, yet comforted her, ſaying,
                            <said>alas! lady, I ſee that this arch prieſt has betrayed you, and brought you in hatred with the emperor; but I'll
                            promiſe you that, if I live, I'll declare all thoſe treacheries to the emperor; and bring the traitor to aſhameful
                            death.</said> So with many thanks for his aid from Blandiman, the merchant departed. THe merchant hacing left them,
                        Blandiman ſet the lady upon her horſe, and himſelf on his, ſo riding on, they came to a lodging in thier way, where they
                        remained eight days, during which time her ſervant was recovered of his wounds, and then ſet forward towards France, paſſing
                        by Orleans, they took their way towards Paris, where king Peping was uſed to ſojourn.</p>
                    <p>Belliſant (as aforeſaid) being with child, was ſuddenly overtaken in the foreſt; the time of her delivery being come, ſhe
                        forſook her horſe, and bid her ſervant lay her ſoftly under a green tree that grew hard by, and make haſte to get her the help
                        of a woman, <said>for I can go no farther, </said><fw type="catch" place="bottom">ſaid</fw><pb n="16"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">16 THE HISTORY OF</fw>ſaid ſhe, <said>my pains ſo increaſe upon me.</said> Blandiman obeyed her commands, and
                        left he ſhould not find the place again, ſet a mark, that he might the readier come thither again, ſo away he went to ſeek
                        ſome woman to help his diſtreſſed lady. He being gone, the lady was left comfortleſs, all alone, and at laſt was delivered of
                        two fair boys, in the deſolate foreſt. Theſe children were no ſooner come into the world, but a freſh miſery happened to this
                        lady; for as ſhe lay under the tree, her two infants by her, ſuddenly came a huge bear, moſt terrible to behold, and took up
                        one of the infants in his mouth, and with great pace haſted into the thickeſt of the foreſt. This ſtrange and unlooked for
                        accident, frighted the diſtreſſed lady to the ſoul, that ſhe cried out moſt lamentably, ſcrambing upon her hands and knees to
                        go after the bear, who was quickly got out of her figut. But, alas! it little availed her, for ſhe never came to the ſight of
                        her child, until by a miracle, it was at length diſclosed. So long wandered this lady up and down, from place to place,
                        weeping for her child, that being weary with travail, ſhe fell ſick and was almoſt <fw type="catch" place="bottom">at</fw><pb
                            n="17"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 17</fw>at the point of death. In this condition we leave her,
                        and porceed to the other child ſhe left under the tree.</p>
                    <p>It happened the ſame day that her brother king Pepin had taken his journey from Paris, towards conſtantinople, to viſit his
                        ſiſter Belliſant; and ſtriking through Orleans, he made ſuch haſte, that he entered into the foreſt where his banished ſiſter
                        was lately delivered of two children, but knew not what happened. Now as the king paſſed through this foreſt, he ſpied lying
                        under a tree, alone, the other ſon of Belliſant; and he ſaid to his attendants, <said>my lords, ſee, I have here found a fair
                            encounter,</said>
                        <said>even a child;</said> ſaid the lords, <said>it is even ſo.</said>
                        <said>Take it up,</said> ſaid the king, <said>it ſhall be brought up at my charge as long as it lives, and be uſed as my own;
                            and ifi t lives to man's eſtate, I'll endow it with lands and poſſeſſions.</said> And calling to one of his 'ſquires, he
                        gave him charge of it, ſaying, <said>take this infant to Orleans, ſee it baptiſed, provide a nurſe for it, and let it want
                            nothing.</said> (The king little ſuſpecting that this child was his nephew.) The 'ſquire took the child to Orleans, had it
                        baptiſed, and gave it his own name, Valentine, and ſought a nurſe, and gave it <fw type="sig" place="bottom">B2</fw><fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">great</fw><pb n="18"/><fw type="header" place="top">THE HISTORY OF</fw>great attendance,
                        according to the king's command. This done, the king proceeded on his journey towards Conſtantinople, to ſee his beauteous
                        ſiſter Belliſant; but ere he could paſs through the foreſt, he chanced to meet with Blandiman, accompanied with a woman that
                        he had brought in order to aſſiſt his lady in her greateſt extremity of child-birth.</p>
                    <p>Bladiman ſeeing the king, knew him, and ſuddenly alighted from his horſe, doing his duty to him. The king perceiving it was
                        Blandiman, aſked what news, and how his ſiſter Belliſant did? Blandiman anſwered, <said>moſt gracious ſovereign, I muſt tell
                            you ſtrange news of your loving ſiſter, and how ſhe fiares: wherefore ſo it is, that by force of treaſon of the arch
                            prieſt of Conſtantinople, ſhe is baniſhed out of the emperor's court and dominions; and, but for the mercy of the lords of
                            the emperor's court and others, ſhe had been burt to aſhes in the ſight of all the people</said></p>
                    <p>King Pepin having heard the lamentable relation of Blandiaman, he broke out in bitter words againſt her, ſaying, <said>I think
                            the emperor no upright judge in ſparing the life of my ſiſter; for I ſwear, that if I had her now in my poſſeſſion, by
                            death I would <fw type="catch" place="bottom">make</fw><pb n="19"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON.
                                19</fw>make her an example to all falſe ladies, whilſt the world enfureth.</said> Then he commanded all his lords and
                        others to ſtay their journey, and return back to Paris; <said>for he grievous offences of my ſiſter, ſtay my journey.</said>
                        And ſo in that diſtruſt and melancholy, king Pepin returned towards Orleans. When Blandiman perceived the king thus angry and
                        ſurpriſed, he durſt proceed no farther in his relation of lady Belliſant, but leaving the king, took his way towards the great
                        tree, where he lately left her in the pains of child-birth; being come thither, he ſought for her every where, but could hear
                        no tidings of her; neither knew he which way to take. Being in this extremity, he tied his horſe to a thorn-tree, and began to
                        make a cloſer ſearch than before, and at length founf her lying flat on the earth, in a manner ſpeechleſs. Blandiman being
                        glad he had founf her, took her up in his arms, and ſet her on her feet, ſaying, <said>alas! dear lady, how came you to ſtray
                            ſo far from the place where I left you?</said></p>
                    <p>The lady replied, <said>"Ah! Blandiman, my diſtreſſes daily increaſe; for thou wert no ſooner gone, but I being delivered of
                            two babes, a ravenous bear aſſailed me, <fw type="cathch" place="bottom">and</fw><pb n="20"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                                >20 THE HISTORY OF</fw>and bore away one of themm and I endeavoured, though in vain, to overtake the ſavage creature,
                            leaving the other infant under the tree."</said>
                        <said>Lady,</said> quoth he, <said>the other infant! Why, I came but lately from the tree, and I am well aſſured there lay no
                            infant there,</said> at which ſhe fell into a ſwoon, and cried out, <said>"come death, and finiſh what sorrows have
                            brought on me."</said></p>
                    <p>All this while Blandiman heard her piteous complaints; at laſt ſhe betaking herſelf to her feet, he accompanied her, with a
                        woman he had brought with him, to a neighbouring village, where they lodged and nouriſhed her, until ſhe had recovered
                        ſtrength. Then Blandiman told her, how he by chance met with her brother, king Pepin; <said>and as ſoon as he underſtood that
                            the emperor had exiled you, he lightly gave credit that you were in the fault, and lays all the blame on you.</said></p>
                    <p><said>"O!</said>quoth the lady, <said>now what I moſt feared is come to paſs— I will never return again to Paris, but take my
                            way into ſome remote land, where my body with my faults ſhall be ſmothered, for my brother's anger is ſo great, that he
                            would willingly deliver me to death, therefore, it is better to fly and ſave my life, than fall into the <fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">fury</fw><pb n="21"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 21</fw>fury of ſo angry a
                            brother."</said>——This ſhe ſpoke with tears. Said Blandiman, <said>lady, dry up your tears, and be aſſured of my
                            fidelity;</said> and ſo they paſſed forth to expoſe themſelves to future dangers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                    <ab>Of the bear that bore away one of the children.</ab>
                    <p>THE bear (as you have heard) that carried away one of the children, all this while had offered it no violence, but bore it to
                        her cave: In this cave the bear had four young ones, among whom ſhe laid the child to be devoured; yet tall this while the
                        young bears did it no harm, but with their rough paws ſtroked it ſoſtly.— The old bear perceiving they did not devour it,
                        ſhewed a beariſh kind of favor towards it, inſomuch that ſhe kept it, and gave it ſuck among her young ones for the ſpace of
                        one year. This child, by reaſon of the nouriſhment it received, became rough all over like a beaſt, and as he grew in
                        ſtrength, began to range up and down <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw><pb n="22"/><fw type="header" place="top">22 THE
                            HISTORY OF</fw>the woods; and when he met with other beaſts would ſmite them, and got ſuch a maſtery over them, that they
                        began to ſhun the place where he came.———And in the beaſt-like eſtate he paſſed theterm of fifteen years, growing up to ſuch a
                        ſtrength, that ſcarce any man or beaſt in the foreſt durſt ſtir abroad leſt he ſhould kill them, and afterwards eat their
                        fleſh. His name was called Orſon, because a bear had been his nurſe.</p>
                    <p>Here we leave the wild man in the foreſt, and look to what became of the lady Belliſant and her ſervant Blandiman, and we will
                        ſuddenly find them wandering through ſeveral lands and countries: the lady ſtill bewailing the loſs of her two children. But
                        in the midſt of her ſorrow, yet paſſed on her weary journey, until at length ſhe came to a port, off Portugal, on which ſtood
                        an invincible caſtle, kept by a giant, called Ferragus, ſo large that there was no horſe to be found that could bear the
                        living trunk of this huge giant. It happened at this caſtle, that every ſhip that paſſed by that port, was to pay tribute to
                        this giant, which he himſelf daily came on voard to receive. At length he came into the ſhip where the <fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">lady</fw><pb n="23"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALWNTINE AND ORSON. 23</fw>lady Belliſant was, and
                        caſting his eyes about, he eſpied her; then kindly taking her by the hand, he led her into the caſtle by this wife, for he was
                        married to a beautiful lady. Blandiman followed his lady alſo, fearing the giant; but he behaved himſelf ſo nobly, that he did
                        not offer her the leaſt violence, but preſented her to his wife, who gladly received her; the giant having charged his wife to
                        uſe her and Blandiman honorably.</p>
                    <p>During their abode in the caſtle, ſhe would often ſhed tears for the loſs of her two children, and the lady of the caſtle would
                        often comfort her in the beſt manner ſhe could. And within this caſtle ſhe tarried a long time: and here we muſt leave her,
                        and return back to tell you ſomething of the emperor of Conſtantinople, and the arch prieſt.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="24"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">24 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                    <ab>How by the counſel of the arch prieſt, new cuſtoms and taxations were raiſed thro' the city of Conſtantinople, and how the
                        treaſon came to light. How the emperor ſent for king Pepin, to ſee the combat fought between the arch prieſt and the
                        merchant.</ab>
                    <p>THE emperor having ſhamefully expelled Belliſant, his wife, often repented him of the fact; and the arch prieſt being an oracle
                        in his ears, inſomuch that he heaped new honors continually upon that traitorous wretch, advencing him above the higheſt in
                        the empire; whatever he commanded was effected. At laſt, having got all power and authority in his own hands, he began to
                        raiſe the cuſtoms and taxes of the city of Conſtantinople, which ſtruck to the hearts of the inhabitants. Amongſt theſe his
                        umpoſitions, it happened that according to their yearly cuſtom, there was held a great mart in the city, which was about the
                        month of September. Hereunto reforted a great number of people, eſpecially merchants. The <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >mart</fw><pb n="25"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 25</fw>mart day being come, the emperor gace the
                        charge thereof to this arch prieſt, who accordingly provided himſelf, and armed two hundred men to guard his own perſon. Being
                        thus accompanied, he took his way into the city.</p>
                    <p>It ſo chanced, that among the reſt of thoſe that ſold wares, the merchant was there preſent, of whom you have heard before,
                        viz. he that came riding by the way where Blandiman, the lady's 'ſquire, and the traitorous arch prieſt were fighting. The
                        arch prieſt perceived him, but took no notice of him, for he was fearful that all his villainy ſhould come to light. The ſight
                        of the merchant much troubled the arch prieſt, ſo that he wiſhed his death, and would have effected the ſame by the authority
                        he now had, but that he feared ſome great tumult would ariſe thereby. Now mark what followed: "The merchant was furniſhed with
                        coſtly wares, as cloth of golf, ſilver, ſilk, &amp;c. and took more money than any five merchants beſide. The fair being
                        ended, the arch prieſt ſent forth his officer to demand his accuſtomed duties. One officer came to the merchand, and ſaid,
                            <said>"Sir, you muſt pay rod <!-- THIS WORD IS WEIRD -->on every pound you have <fw type="sig" place="bottom">C</fw><fw
                                type="catch" place="bottom">taken,</fw><pb n="26"/><fw type="header" place="top">26 THE HISTORY OF</fw>takenm it being
                            o ordered by the offieers <!-- this is weird too --> to whom it belongs."</said> He at this being angry, ſaid,
                            <said>curſed be the diſloyal arch prieſt, for he is the only cauſe of theſe new raiſed exactions; it had been well if he
                            had long ſince had his deſert, and with ſhame and infamy ended his days.</said> At which reporachful words, the officer
                        took his ſtaff and ſtruck the merchant on the head, ſo that presently the blood guſhed out: then the merchant drew his ſword,
                        and truck the officer, ſo that he laid him at his feet for dead.</p>
                    <p>Upon this aroſe a gret rout through the fair, inſomuch that the other officers, coming up to help their fellow, took the
                        merchant and carried him before the arch prieſt. The arch prieſt would have put him to death, but the merchany appealed to
                        juſtice to have his cauſe tried by law. The arch prieſt fearing the people, ſent him away to the emperor: for nothing could
                        ſatisfy him but his life; but in ſeeking the life of the merchant, he perchaſed his own death. The emperor in perſon ſat as
                        judge, and the arch prieſt brought his advocate to plead his cauſe, which was, <hi>"That the merchangt had committed murder,
                            and had ſpoken opprobious words againſt the <fw type="catch" place="bottom">arch</fw><pb n="27"/><fw type="header"
                                place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 27</fw>arch prieſt."</hi> The advocate having ended his accuſation, the merchant fell
                        on his knees before the emperor, and ſaid, <hi><said>"Moſt excellent prince, give me but audience, and I ſhall unfold a matter
                                of ſuch importance, that it touches yourperſon in the higheſt degree of treaſon."</said></hi>
                        <said>Say on,</said> ſaid the emperor, <hi><said>"mighty emperor, I adviſe you to make faſt the gates about your palace, that
                                none depart this place."</said></hi> The emperor did as he requeſted. <said>Then,</said> ſaid the merchant, <said>"all
                            you that love the honor of the emperor, attend my words; the time is come that the treaſon of the curſt atch prieſt will
                            be revealed, and come to light: great emperor, this is that curſed man that you have nouriſhed and brought to great honor,
                            who hath deceived his truſt; for he it is that hath wrought all the diſcord between you and your virtuous lady whom you
                            have baniſhed from your bed, and by whom you have received more diſhonor, than he ever recieved honor from you; for he
                            ſecretly , and underhandedly, made love to the empreſs: but ſhe denied him; and he perceiving there was no likelihood to
                            accompliſh his deſire, it drove him into fearthat his diſloyal act would come to light, and therefore deviſed to flaſify
                            unto your <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ears</fw><pb n="28"/><fw type="header" place="top">28 THE HISTORY OF</fw> ears
                            her unfaithful love to your bed. All which his falſe accuſations, I will here unfold the truth of what theſe eyes were
                            witneſſes.</said></p>
                    <p><said>It happened on a day, after the baniſhment of the empreſs, as I was riding about my affairs, I chanced to travel thro' a
                            wood, and found the treacherous prieſt transformed out of the habit of a prieſt into that of a knight, ready for combatl
                            Drawing nearer, I beheld him fighting with another man armed; who, at laſt, I found to be Blandiman, 'ſquire to the
                            baniſhed lady, who conducted her in the time of her exile. I perceiving they encountered each other ſo fiercely, I called
                            to them to give over, but thy little regarded me. I perceived the lady weeping, and at laſt ſhe ſaid unto me,
                                    <hi><said>"gentle merchant, aſſiſt me againſt this treacherous arch prieſt, that ſeeketh by force to rob me of my
                                    honor: This is he by whom I am baniſhed from my emperor's bed and country."——</said></hi> With that I put ſpurs to
                            my horſe, and ran between them to part them: which the arch prieſt preceiving, he fled into the wood. I well knowing who
                            he was, noble emperor, it had been my part to have revealed this long ago, but durſt not, for fear <fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">his</fw><pb n="29"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 29</fw>his greatness ſhould have
                            brought me to an untimely death.</said></p>
                    <p>The emperor hacing heard all this, he ſighed, and at laſt fell into tears:—then turned to the arch prieſt, ſaying,
                                <hi><said>"well I have ſeen now what I have ever miſtruſted! Thou haſt made me of all men moſt unhappy!—Thy treaſon
                                hath bewitched me, in an evil hour I gace credit to thy falſe tongue!"</said></hi></p>
                    <p>The emperor ſeeing the merchant ſo reſolute, he ſaid, <said>"arch prieſt, it is time that thou either acquit thyſelf by
                            anſwering this challenge, or yeild theyſelf guilty of what has been laid to thy charge."</said> The arch prieſt replied,
                            <said>"mighty emperor, to anſwer to the merchant's challenge is con<fw type="sig" place="bottom">C2</fw><fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">trary</fw><pb n="30"/><fw type="header" place="top">30 THE HISTORY OF</fw>trary to my place and
                            calling, for I am a ſacred prelate of the church, and therefore I may refuſe to fight."</said>
                        <hi><said>"Nay,</said> ſaid the emperor, <said>in this caſe no excuſe is to be admitted; but you muſt either fight or yeild
                                yourſelf a traitor to my crown and dignity."</said></hi> At theſe words the arch prieſt was ſore troubled in mind,
                        yet, at laſt, he was fain to accept the combat. So the emperor commanded them both to ſafe keeping, until he had ſent letters
                        to king Pepin of France.</p>
                    <p>The ambaſſadors, after long travel, arrived at Tome, where they found king Pepin; the ambaſſadors then ſaid, <hi><said>"great
                                lord, we preſent theſe letters from Alexander your brother, emperor of Conſtantinople, of which we entreat a ſpeedy
                                anſwer."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>King Pepin took the letters graciouſly, and read them, after which he ſaid, <said>"my lords, the emperor ſends me word, that my
                            ſiſter Belliſan has been wrongfully baniſhed; and that, by reaſon of a falſe arch prieſt, to whom he gave too much truſt;
                            which prieſt, for theſe treaſonable facts, is accuſed by a merchant, who has challenged this treacherous prieſt to ſingle
                            combat. Now the day and place is ready for the trial of this fact, whereby I <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ſhall</fw><pb
                                n="31"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 31</fw>ſhall be fully ſatisfied, whether my ſiſter has been
                            guilty of what she has been charged with, and ſhamefully baniſhed for. Upon all which, I ſwear and vow by my crown and
                            dignity, that if the emperor has offered this indignity without cauſe, I will be revenged of him in the extremeſt manner
                            that war can thunder forth."</said> Having ended his ſpeech to his lords, in the preſence of the ambaſſadors, he commanded
                        that every man ſhould accompany him to Conſtantinople, to behold this fight between the merchant and the arch prieſt.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                    <ab>How the merchant and the arch prieſt encountered about the clearing of the lady Belliſant; and what a glorious victory did
                        betide the merchant.</ab>
                    <p>NOW was the day appointed come for the combat between the arch prieſt and the merchant; and every thing was in readineſs,
                        according to the command of the emperor. At last came both com<fw type="catch" place="bottom">batants</fw><pb n="32"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">32 THE HISTORY OF</fw>batants into the fild, and preſented themſelves before the emperor. The
                        arch prieſt was armed in a most ſumptuous armour of preoof, all emboſſed with gold and pearl, that it dazzled the eyes of the
                        beholders. The arch prieſt came forth in the field, and took his place appointed him at one end of the lift. The emperor
                        beholding the glorious ſhow that the arch prieſt made in his arms, called forthe the merchant cauſing him firſted to kneel
                        down, and in the preſence of the aſſembly dybbed him knight: Then he commanded that a rich armour ſhould be put on him, in the
                        preſence of king Pepin, who during the time he was arming, promiſed this merchant if he overcame the arch prieſt, to advance
                        him to great livings and high authority.</p>
                    <p>Theſe two adverſaries being now in redineſs, their horſes were brought forth, and they mounted, ready to give battle. The
                        emperor gave ſtrict charge to all his officers of arms, to have a ſpecial eye upon the arch prieſt, leſt he ſhould fly the
                        field, or run away from them. The merchant being mounted, and his ſword girt on him, firſt entered the liſts; then came the
                        arch prieſt, accompanied with nobels of great honor and dignity. The combatants thus <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >entered</fw><pb n="33"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 33</fw>entered the liſts, ready to charge each
                        other; king Pepin called out aloud to the merchant, ſaying, <said>My friend, may God give thee victory over this falſe
                            traitor:</said> The merchant replied, <said>Dread king, I doubt not but this might to make this traitorous prieſt confeſs,
                            that he has villanouſly ſought the deſtruction of your ſiſter.——</said> Then came a herald, and adminiſtered to them both
                        an oath; and after clearing the lifts, left the champions to their fortunes. The marſhals of the field brought each of them a
                        ſpear, which they had no ſooner recieved, but they put ſpurs to their horſes, and ran with ſuch violence together, that their
                        ſpears were broken in their hands: then they ſet forward for another courſe, charging each other with their ſwords, in ſuch a
                        violent manner, that they cut off hwole quarters of the croſſets: the arch prieſt ſeeing himſelf ſo ſtiffly matched, gave over
                        the fight until towards evening, for ſuch was the cuſtom of the country, thinking thereby to weary out the merchant; which the
                        merchant perceiving, he prepared to meet the arch prieſt courageouſly when he encountered him, which being not long after the
                        merchant ſo redoubled his ſtrokes, that he cut off one of his <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ears;</fw><pb n="34"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">34 THE HISTORY OF</fw>ears; and with the violence of the ſame blow, the merchant's ſword fell
                        from his hand; which the arch prieſt ſeeing, put ſpurs to his horſe, and charged him with ſuch violence, that he ran againſt
                        the merchant;s horſe, and thruſt out one of his eyes; the horſe feeling himself hurt, ran up and down as mad, leaping ſo
                        furiouſly that he threw his rider; the merchant's foor hung in the ſtirrup, whereby he was in great danger. King Pepin was ſo
                        diſcouraged at this diſaſter, that the tears trickled down his cheeks.</p>
                    <p>Now that which was more miraculous was, that all the time the merchant was dragged up and down the field, with his foot hanging
                        in the ſtirrup, the arch prieſt could not force his horſe forward, btu fled to and fro, ſo that he could not make a prey of
                        the merchant, as he intended. But at laſt the merchant's horſe fell down, and he got his foot clear of the ſtirrup.</p>
                    <p>The prieſt perceiving he had recovered his legs, ran with violence upon him, and gave him five or ſix ſuch blows upon his
                        ſhoulders, that the poor merchant was aſtonished. At laſt he was forced to give back, to recover breath; and in a little time
                        he gave a freſh aſſault upon the arch <fw type="catch" place="bottom">prieſt</fw><pb n="35"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                            >VALENTINE AND ORSON. 35</fw>prieſt with ſuch violence that the ſword fell out of his hand; but he at firſt ſo wounded
                        him, that the blood rant through his armour upon the earth. This ſo vexed the prieſt, that he grew mad with rage, and turned
                        his horſe upon the merchant, thinking to have over-run him; but the merchant obſering his drift, prepared to receive him, and
                        drawing a long knife, punched it into the belly of the horſe, which made him fling and leadp, ſo that the prieſt was like to
                        have been unhorſed, and ſtriving to ſabe himſelf, he loſt his ſhield. The merchant ſeeing him unarmed, ran haſtily and caught
                        up his ſhield, and caſt it awayl and then making towards his horſe, ſmote him hin the belly with his ſword, which brought both
                        horſe and rider to the ground.</p>
                    <p>The prieſt being thus unhorſed, endeavored to recover himſelf; but the merchant gave him sucj a blow, that he laid him flat to
                        the ground again, and leaping on him, pulled off his helmet, thinking to have ſmitten off his head. The atch prieſt ſeeing
                        himſelf in ſuch danger, ſaid, <said>I pray thee, friend, take pity on me, and give me leave to confeſs myſeld; for I yeild
                            myſelf vanquiſhed.</said> The merchant was <fw type="catch" place="bottom">very</fw><pb n="36"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">36 THE HISTORY OF</fw>very corteous, and granted his requſt. The arch prieſt was no ſooner got on his feet,
                        but claſping the merchant in his arms, threw him on the ground, and leaping upon him, ſaying to the merchant, <said>I have now
                            an advantage over thee, and thou ſhalt not eſcape with life, if thou doſt not effect what I command thee.</said>
                        <said>Ah!</said> ſaid the merchant, <said>haſt thou betrayed me? well, I ſtand at thy mercy; therefore let me know what thou
                            commandeſt.</said>
                        <said>Then,</said> ſaid the prieſt, <said>go with me to the emperor and king Pepin, and teſtify that thou haſt falſely accuſed
                            me; which if thou wilt do, I promiſe thee to ſabe thy life.</said> The merchant having heard what the prieſt ſaid, was
                        very ſorrowful; but at length he thus answered, <said>ſir, prieſt, I am ready to accompliſh thy deſires, ſo let us go to the
                            emperor, and there I will ſet you free from all the accuſations which I have exhibited againſt you.</said>
                        <said>Very well,</said> ſaid the arch prieſt, <said>then let us go together.</said></p>
                    <p>The merchant had no ſooner got on his feet, but he began afreſh to pen the treason of the arch prieſt, even to his teethl and
                        again he took courage, and ſuddenly claſping the arch prieſt in his arms, threw him on the ground, and having him at <fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">advantage</fw><pb n="37"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 37</fw>advantage,
                        he ſaid, <said>arch prieſt, ſeeing that you have taught me to play my pary, think no more on confeſſions, for you ſhall
                            confeſs to me, or none.</said> The arch prieſt ſeeing himſelf beat at his own weapons, began agian to entreat; but the
                        merchant not regarding him, preſently put out his eyes, and gave him ſo many deadly blows, that he ſecured him from doing him
                        any further harm. Then the merchant called the marſhals of the field, and ſaid, <hi><said>"Lo, here you may ſee I have done my
                                endeavour againſt the arch prieſt; and if he is vanquiſhed, ſay ſo: And my requeſt is, that you would conduct
                                Alexander, the emperor of Conſtantinople, and king Pepin of France, to this place, that they may be
                                ear-witneſſes<!-- not sure if this is correct hyphenation --> of the confeſſion which the arch prieſt ſhall make to
                                them."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>The marſhals did according to the requeſt of the merchant , and perſently the emperor and king Pepin went to the place where
                        the arch prieſt lay vanquiſhed.</p>
                    <p>When the emperor and the king, with the reſt of the nobles, had head the vilainout prieſt acknowledged that the empreſs was
                        entirely innocent, and that the wicked plot was all of his own forming, who can expreſs the joy and ſorrow of <fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">D</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">theſe</fw><pb n="38"/><fw type="header" place="top">38 THE HISTORY
                            OF</fw>theſe two mighty potentates, and of the reſt of the aſſembly?</p>
                    <p>The firſt thing that was determined, was the execution of this wicked prieſt, which being finiſhed, the emperor came to king
                        Pepin, and in the moſt friend'y and passionate manner, endeavored to excuſe himſeld to him for the siſgrace of his ſiſter;
                        vowing, as a true mark of the ſenſe of his indeiſcretion, he would be his ſervant to the end of his life; upon whic ha
                        perpetual peace was made between them; and king Pepin, but not without ſome heavy cognitations, ſet forward for his own
                        country.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                    <ab>How Haufrey and Henry repined at the king's love to Valentine.</ab>
                    <p>IT happened one day, when the king was at dinner, and Valentine was attending upon him, that the king called to him, and in
                        hearing of all his nobles, told him, that he was indebted to him for the preſervation of his life, and for many other ſignal
                        acts of duty and ſervice; and that in conſideration thereof, he freely gave him the earldom of Clair<fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">mond,</fw><pb n="39"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 39</fw>mond, and would be ſure to
                        ſhew him further marks of his favor, the firſt opportunity.</p>
                    <p>This new decalration fo the king's, gave the two brothers, Haufrey and Henry, freſh cauſe for malice and jealouſy, inſomuch
                        that they contrived daily plots to take away his life; which Valentine not ſuſpecting, went on cheerfully in the king's
                        ſervice, and grew every day more and more in his favor. But leave we at this preſent, to return a little to his brother Orſon,
                        againſt whom ſuch frequent complaints were brought to court, that the king, with the advice of his nobles, iſſued out his
                        proclaimation, whth a reward of two thouſand crowns for any that ſhould take this furious wild man, either alive or dead, and
                        bring his head before him.</p>
                    <p>Hereupon aſſembled many knights to take this affair in hand; and whilſt the king was debating with them, Haufrey , Valentine's
                        enemy, being there, propoſed to the king to ſend Valentine, <said>who having offered unlawful love to your daughter Eglantin,
                            he is the fitteſt to fight this ſavage, whom, if he vanquiſhes, let him have her in marriage.</said>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw></p>
                    <pb n="40"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">40 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine conquers Orſon, his brother, a wild man in the woods of Orleans, and preſents him to king Pepin.</ab>
                    <p>NOW Valentine whent on his journey, and ſoon arrived in the foreſt; but it being night, he tied his horſe to a tree and betook
                        himſelf to the top for his ſecurity. As ſoon as it was day, looking round him, he ſaw his brother Orſon coming towards him,
                        and coming to the tree where the horſe was tied, and having never ſeen ſuch a horſe before, he began to ſcratch and tear him
                        with his nails; upon which the horſe grew mad, and kicked at him with great fury.</p>
                    <p>Valentine perceiving his horſe in danger, cried out aloud, and ſaid, <said>"wild man, leave my horſe."</said> The wild man,
                        hearing a ſtrange voice, looked up to the tree, and ſeeing a man, made divers ſigns for him to come down. Valentine making all
                        the haſte he could, drew his ſword, which when Orſon ſaw, he leaped back, but ſuddenly returned again upon Valentine, and
                        threw him on the ground. Being thus grovelling on the ground, Valen<fw type="catch" place="bottom">tine</fw><pb n="41"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 41</fw>tine eſſayed divers times to have gotten Orſon under him. When he
                        ſaw that by strength there was no hope to overcome him, he pulled out a ſharp pointed knige, and ſmote Orſon in the ſide; he
                        ſeeing himſelf wounded, fiercely aſſulted Valenine with his ſharp nails: They fought ſo long together, that it is too tedious
                        here to relate; however, ſo long, that they both gre faint. In which tediouſneſs, bothe ſtanding gaping upon each other,
                        Valentine looked ſtedfaſtly upon him, made ſigns to him he would give him food and raiment befitting a human creature. Orſon
                        understood his meaning, and made ſigns also, that he would obey him in every thing he deſired. And thus Valentine conquered
                        the wild man.</p>
                    <p>All this adventure being ended in this manner, he took Orſon by the hand, and ſhewed him ſigns that he ſhould go on before him
                        until they were out of the wood, for he would not truſt him behind; and being out of the wood, Valentine took off one of his
                        girths, and bound his hands ſaſt, that he ſhould not attempt to fo him any hurt; and in this manner he mounted on horſe-back,
                        and led the wild man after him. <fw type="sig" place="bottom">D2</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">Valentine</fw><pb n="42"
                            /><fw type="header" place="top">42 THE HISTORY OF</fw><!-- MISSING PAGESSSSS -->Valentine took his way towards Orleans,
                        but you muſt imagine he could not reach thither in one day, therefore he reſolved to lodge at the next village. But the
                        inhabitants perceiving the wild man, they retired into their houſed and ſhut up their doors. Valentine cried out to them,
                                <hi><said>"open your doors every man, fear not, for we are come only for lodgings;"</said></hi> yet for all this they
                        would not. Valentine, by ſigns, bid the wild man break open one of the gates of an inn, which he did, into which they entered.
                        Valentine went into which they entered. Valentine went into the ſtable and ſet upon his horſe; and Orſon in the mean time,
                        went into the kitchen, where there were capons, and other proviſons, upon a ſpit roaſting. Valentine made ſigns that he ſhould
                        turn the ſpit; but he not underſtanding the meaning, ſet his talons spon the meat, and tore it from the ſpit, and in a greedy
                        manner devoured the ſpit, and in a greedy manner devoured it; and ſeeing a chaldron of water ſtanding by he put his head into
                        it and drank. Valentine perceiving him to be athriſt, made ſigns to him to foeſake the water, and he would give him wine.
                        Orſon drank ſo freely of the wine, that he became intoxicated, and throwing himself on the floor, ſlept, as his cuſtom was ,
                        like a wild beaſt in the foreſt.<!-- there might be a signature??? --><fw type="catch" place="bottom">Now</fw></p>
                    <p><pb n="43"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 43</fw>Now the morning being come, Valentine betook himſelf to
                        his horſe, and led the wild man bound towards Orleans, where when they arrived, the city was all in an uproar, and forſook
                        their houſes for fear of him. </p>
                    <p>By this time tidings came to king Pepin, that Valentine had conquered the wildman, and had brought him to Orleans. Valentine
                        rode through the city, until he came to the palace gate of the king; and when the proter ſaw Orſon, he ſhut the gates upon
                        them, 'till he bid them go and tell the king, he need be under no apprehenſions for fear of the wild man, for he would hurt
                        nobody. So Valentine took him by the hand and led him into the court, where the king, accompanied with his nobels, kindly
                        welcomed him home. The king viewed the wild man narrowly, and ſaid, that he was of fair ſtature, and if he were clothed and
                        armed he would appear like a worthy knight.</p>
                    <p>Says Valentine, <said>my liege, I think it is proper he were baptiſed; which being donw and ſupper ended, they all went to
                            thier reſpective apartments, and Valentine and Orſon were appointed to a fair chamber and bed, but as ſoon as Orſon
                            entered, he laid down on the ground, and fell aſleep.</said><fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <fw type="header" place="top">44 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                    <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
                    <ab>How Haufrey and Henry conſpired to murder Valentine, and how duke Savery ſent to king Pepin for did againſt the green knight,
                        who threatened to marry his daughter againſt his will.</ab>
                    <p>SO glad and joyful was the lady Eglantine, that Valentine had conquered the wild man, that ſhe ſent him word to bring the wild
                        man to her. Then he took Orſon by the hand and led him to her, where were aſſembled divers ladies to behild him; and Orſon
                        entertained them with ſeveral diverting ſigns and geſtures.——While this aſſembly were in Eglantine's chamber, Haufrey came to
                        Henry, and ſaid to him, <said>"brother, you ſee how the honor of this foundling increaſeth; therefore let us lay a plot to
                            deſtroy him."</said> Accordingly they put it in action, and ruſhed into the chamber. As ſoon as Haufrey was catered, he
                        thus began with Valentine:<!-- This might not be a said tag --><hi><said>Diſloyal man, new ſhalt thou know the price of thy
                                inconſtancy, by abuſing our ſiſter;</said></hi> then giving him at the ſame time, a mighty blow with his fiſt upon the
                        face, ſo that the blood ran out of his <fw type="catch" place="bottom">mouth;</fw><pb n="45"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                            >VALENTINE AND ORSON. 45</fw>mouth; Henry on the other hand, thought to have ſmitten him too with a glace to the ground,
                        but Orſon perceived they were in earneſt, leaped out, and gave Haufrey ſuch a ſtroke with his rough fiſt, that he felled him;
                        after ran Henry and girded him ſo between his arms, that if the ladies had not been preſent to have appeaſed his wrath, he had
                        deſtroyed them both.</p>
                    <p>This cauſed an outcry thro' the whole court. Haufrey and Henry went to their father, making complaint againſt Valentine and the
                        wild man. The long hearing their complaint, was ſorry, and gave orders that Orſon ſhould be put into a ſtrong tower, and not
                        come abroad without leave; and then ſent to Valentine, to know the true cauſe of his diſorder: who, when he came before the
                        king, and had related all circumſtances, then ſaid the king, <hi><said>Orſon has done nothing but right; and as for you, I
                                vow, I would not loſe him for the beſt baron in my land; for I have made many trials of his love and fathfulneſs
                                towards me.</said></hi> And with this anſwer, Haufrey and Henry ſtraitway departed. <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >Not</fw></p>
                    <p><pb n="46"/><fw type="header" place="top">46 THE HISTORY OF</fw>Not long after the coming of Valentine and Orſon to court, the
                        duke Saviry ſent certain meſſengers to king Pepin, which ſaid unto him, <hi><said>" great king, our duke has ſent us to you,
                                to requeſt your aid againſt a falſe pagan, called the green knight, who has beſieged his confines, and intends to have
                                his daughter by force of arms."</said></hi> The king promiſed the meſſenger that he would agree to aſſiſt the duke;
                        but ſcarace had he made this promiſe, when news came to court of another meſſenger from Lyons, which brought advice, that the
                        Almains were coming againſt him with a great army.</p>
                    <p>The king was very much troubled at this, and preſently called his nobles, and craved their conuſel, wherein it was reſolved,
                            <said>" that the army ſhould forthwith march againſt the Almains. The duke, I confeſs, deſerves to e ſuccoured, but yet in
                            two extremes, let us chuſe to defend out own country."</said></p>
                    <p>Now, gentle reader, I'll let you underſtand, this green knight was the brother to Ferragus, the giant that kept the lady
                        Belliſant in his caſtle, who was mother to Valentine and Orſon, as it is before declared.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Duke</fw>
                    <pb n="47"/>
                    <p><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 47</fw>Duke Davory having no hope of aid from king Pepin, made open
                        procalmation thro' all his diminions, that all the men ſhould be ready armed againſt to-morrow, for he would then try his
                        ſucceſs againſt the green knight. The day being come, both armies met, and the green knight behaved himſelf so valiantly, that
                        in the firſt encounter he ſlew two knights. Duke Savory ſeeing him ſo valiant a general, came up to encounter him, without
                        conſidering what was commonly ſaid of him, which was, <said>"that he ſhould never be vanquiſhed of any, except one who had
                            never ſucked the breaſt of a woman."</said></p>
                    <p>The green knight triumphed over the worthy duke; brought him to his pavilion, and reviled him in this manner: <hi><said>Duke,
                                now art thou my vaſſal, and I have power over thy life; either give me thy daughter Fezon to wife, of elſe I'll take
                                her by force; and except thou yield to my demand, I'll make thee finiſh thy days miſerably, and conſume all Aquitain
                                to aſhes.</said></hi> To which the duke replied, <hi><said>"Proud pagan, the God's protect me from thy cruelty; for I
                                would rather rely on thier power than thine."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>Says the green knight, <said>"I am not aſhamed to let you underſtand that thy daughter's beauty hath enthralled me, and I will
                                <fw type="catch" place="bottom">recal</fw><pb n="48"/><fw type="header" place="top">THE HISTORY OF</fw>recal thy
                            threatened ſentence, provided that thou, within the ſpace of ſix months, find out a champion that ſhall vanquiſh me in
                            ſingle combat; but if it happen that I prove conqueror, then ſhalt thou give thy daughter to be my lawful
                        wife."</said></p>
                    <p>Theſe conditions being agreed on, duke Savory repaired to Aquitain, whither heis ſaid daughter; and the truce being taken for
                        ſix months, meſſengers wer ſent into all countries, with the following advertiſment:
                            <!-- should this have a said because we know it is an ad? --><hi>"That if there were any man that dare encounter the green
                            knight for the love of fair Fezon, he ſhould lay down his gauge."</hi></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. X.</head>
                    <ab>How Orſon encountered the green knight; alſo, how Valentine attempted to fight him, but without ſucceſs.</ab>
                    <!-- It feels like there is a gap in the story here -->
                    <p>ORSON perceiving the green knight diſpleaſed, and to threaten him, threw down his hood, and Valentine told him, it was a token
                        that he challenged him to combat on the morrow. The green knight en<fw type="catch" place="bottom">raged</fw><pb n="49"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON 49</fw>raged threat, ſwore by Mahomet, that before the morrow's ſun was ſet,
                        he would hang him on a tree higher than any of the reſt; and with theſe words left the duke's caſtle and betook himſelf to his
                        pavilion.</p>
                    <p>They paſſed the reſt of the night in merriments, and ſo went to bed. Morning being come, they all went into the hall, where it
                        was agreed that Galeram, a worthy knight of France, ſhould he the firſt that fought the green knight; who no ſooner ſaw him
                        approach, but he ſet ſpurs on his horſe, and encountered the famous Galeram ſo fiercely that he ſmote him to the earth, and
                        after hanged him on a tree, as he had done many before. Orſon preceiving this, made ſigns that he would fight him preſently;
                        but Valentine, by ſigns, told him he would go and try his own ſtrength firſt on him, and taking leave of the beauteous lady
                        Fezon, he mounted his horſe, and took his way towards the tent. When the green knight eſpied him, he was more fearful of him
                        than of the reſt, wherefore he ſaid, <said>ſir knight, hearken to me,—on yonder tree there hangs a green ſheild, in which
                            remaineth ſuch virtue, that until ſome knight can fetch it from thence, I can never be overcome; and further I aſſure
                            thee, ex<fw type="sig" place="bottom">E</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">cept</fw><pb n="50"/><fw type="header"
                                place="top">50 THE HISTORY OF</fw>cept he be the ſon of a king, and ſuch a one as never ſucked the breast of a woman,
                            I can never be vanquiſhed.</said></p>
                    <p>At theſe words, Valentien, with a loud voice, ſpake thus; <said>whoſoever I am, I will not depart hence until I have fought
                            you.</said> Upon which the green knight mounted his horſe immediately, and both ran the courſe with ſuch fury, that their
                        ſpears were ſhivered in many pieces; after this they drew their ſwords, and began a moſt bloody and deſperate fight, which
                        continued ſo long ,that the day began to ſhutin, and both gre waery; when the green knight, in a haughty manner, told
                        Valentine it was proper for them to leave off the fight until to-morrow; and go, ſaid he, to the city of Aquitain, and report
                        that I eſteem thee the moſt valiant knight that I ever encountered, but meet me in the morning, and then we will end the
                        combat.</p>
                    <p>Valentine accepted this offer, and ſo retruned to the city, where he was with great joy received by the duke Savory, the lady
                        Fezon, but more particularlt by Orſon, who caught him in his arms; being come into the palace, the duke demanded what tidings
                        from the green knight; <said>ſir,</said> ſaid Valentine, <said>he reſteth in his pacilior <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                                >and</fw><pb n="51"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON 51</fw>and I think, he is of that ſtrength,
                            that there is not a man living able to vanquiſh him.</said>
                        <said>Valentine,</said> quoth the duke, <said>you have eſcaped well, for ever did any return, wherefore you have proved
                            yourſeld a valiany knight.</said> Having ended the conference with the ducke, Valentine was unarmed and conducted to the
                        chamber of the lady Fezon.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine ſent Orſon on the morrow to fight the green knight; and how Orſon overcame him.</ab>
                    <p>VALENTINE having ſeriously conſidered that it was impoſſible for him to vanquiſh the green knight, concludes it more proper to
                        put Orſon in his armour, and ſend him on the morrow to try the combat; whichwhen by ſigns he had let him know, he was
                        exceedingly rejoiced, but denied taking Valentine's horſe and armour, deſiring only a club, ſuch a one he was accuſtomed to.
                        Valentine ſeeing this, told him that he muſt put on the ſame armour, and ride on the ſame horſe, for that the knight ſhould
                        not know but <fw type="catch" place="bottom">that</fw><pb n="52"/><fw type="header" place="top">52 THE HISTORY OF</fw>that it
                        was Valentine that came againſt him, to which Orſon agreed; but before he took horſe, he went and took leave of the lady
                        Fezon, and ſo ride directly to the pavillion of the green knight, and ſmote the top thereof with his ſpear, in token of
                        defiance. The green knight being moved at this rough ſalutation, ſwore by Mahomet, that he would fetter his pride before
                        evening, ſo mounted his ſteed, and couched his ſpear; they ran the firſt courſe with ſuch force, that both horſes and men fell
                        to the ground; from whence having recovered themſelves, drew their ſwords and laid upon one another fiercely.</p>
                    <p>The green knight being fired with anger, ſmote Orſon with ſuch a blow, that he cut a peice of his ſhield quite away, and
                        wounded him deeply; when the fierceneſs of the ſtroke the ſword fell out of his hand. Orſon ſeeing the blood run down, gave
                        the giant ſuch a pat on his head, that it entered the fleſh, and his ſword ſliding from his head, took his arm ſo powerfully,
                        that the blood flowed in abundance; but the green knight, by virtue of a ſovereign balſam, which he always carried about him,
                        cured it in an inſtant.</p>
                    <p>Upon this Orſon threw away his armour and wwapons, and ſuddenly ran upon him <fw type="catch" place="bottom">and</fw><pb n="53"
                            /><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 53</fw>and caſt him to the ground, and held him ſo down, that the
                        green knight did yield to his mercy; Orſon not regarding his ſubmiſſion, would have teken away his life, had not Valentine
                        come at the very inſtant and prevented him. <said>You ſee,</said> ſays Valentine, <said>that oyou are in the hands of your
                            enemy, wherefore I think it fit that you ſudder preſent death, and be hanged on the higheſt branch of yonder tree, except
                            you agree to theſe conditions; <hi>"That you renounce paganiſm; go with me to Prance and tell king Pepin that by Valentine
                                and Orſon you were covercome in ſingle combat."</hi></said>To all which he readily agreed.</p>
                    <p>Then Valentine made ſigns to Orſon to let him riſe; being upon his feet, he requested Valentine to ſend him to the tree,
                            <said>and if he bring away the ſhield there faſtened, then I am aſſuredhi is the man that ſhould conquer me:</said> Orſon
                        accordingly didl which when the green knight ſaw, he threw himself at his feet, and would have kiſſed them; <hi><said>"I am
                                well aſſure that you are the braveſt knight in the world.</said></hi></p>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">E2</fw>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb n="54"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">54 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                    <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
                    <ab>Hoe king Pepin came to know that Valentine and Orſon were his nephews; and how the green knight ſubmitted himſelf according to
                        his promiſe.</ab>
                    <p>BLANDIMAN having delivered his meſſage, the king demanded where his ſiſter was? <said>My lord,</said> ſaid Blandiman,
                            <said>I'll relae to you the while ſtory: <hi>"Your ſiſter, who was unjuſtly baniſhed, in her journey, was delivered of two
                                ſons in the foreſt of Orleand; while ſhe ſent me for help, one of them was carried away by a bear in the wood, ſhe
                                knew not whither; ſhe floowed it for ſo long, that at laſt I dound he in a ſwoon upon the ground; but ſhe coming to
                                herſelf, told what had happened; ſo I haſtened to the tree where I left her, but could not find the other child: And
                                thus, worthy king, I have told you the while ſtory."—</hi></said>The king replied, <said>what you have told me,
                            Blandiman, fills me full of a thouſand imaginations; this Valentine and Orſon whom I had in my court, muſt be the empreſs,
                            my ſiſter's ſons; one I foun myſelf in the wood, whom I carefully bred up to <fw type="catch" place="bottom">man's</fw><pb
                                n="55"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 55</fw>man's eſtate; and the other, being utterly wild and
                            ſavage, was conquered by his brother, and brought to court.</said></p>
                    <p>At theſe tidings the court was joyful, onlu Haufrey and Henry, whoſehatred was implacable against Valentine. But to keep up to
                        the ſtory, Blandiman hearing the king ſpeak ſo particularly of the children, took the liberty to aſk the king, if he knew into
                        what country they were gone? To whom the king made anſwer, that they took their way towards Aquitain, to fight a champion,
                        called the green knight, for the love of lady Fexon, only daughter to duke Savory, prince of the country.</p>
                    <p>Soon after the green knight arrived at Paris. The king ſeeing him in armour; marvelled thereat, demanding the cauſe of his ſo
                        appearing; who he was, and from whence he acem? <said>I am that pagan knight, that for the love of lady Fezon, daughter to the
                            duke Aquitain, have for one whole year holden him in ſubjection, and at the ſame time conditioned with him that if he
                            could find out a knight, within the ſpace of ſix months, that could vanquiſh me in ſingle combat, I would raiſe my ſiege,
                            and depart out of hie territories; but, on the contrarym he ſhould de<fw type="catch" place="bottom">liver</fw><pb n="56"
                                /><fw type="header" place="top">56 THE HISTORY OF</fw>liver me his daughter to be my lawful wife.</said></p>
                    <p><said>At laſt aſſailed me, two worthy knights, the one named Valentine, the nother Orſon. Valentine fought me one whole
                            day;—night coming on, we were forced to give over, without putting an end to the combat; the next morning his fellow
                            Orſon, armed in Valentine's armour, entered the feild, in a moſt fierce and diſdainful manner, againſt whom I addreſſed
                            myſelf, but to no purpoſe, for in the end he overcame me, and would have taken away my life, had not Valentine come in
                            upon us, and reſcued me, upon condition that I ſhould renounce paganiſm, and be baptiſed, and then ſurrender myſelf at
                            your command, and to be dealt with as your majeſty ſhall think proper.</said></p>
                    <p>The king having head all this long ſtory, made this anſwer; <said>welcome to us, live with us in our court, for I freely grant
                            you your life, and promiſe you, that if you tarry with us in ourcountry, I will endow thee with many fair lands and
                            poſſeſſions:</said> The king ſhowing himſelf thus gracious, demanded of him where theſe knights were that had conquered
                        him?—Quoth the green knight, <said>I left them both at Aquitain, with the caliant duke Savory. <lb/><fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">And</fw><pb n="57"/><fw type="header" place="bottom">VALENTINE AND ORSON, 57</fw><lb/></said>And thus,
                        by the words of Blandiman and the green knight, the king came to the knowledge, that Valentine and Orſon were his nephews, and
                        the ſons of the emperoro of Greece; the tidings of which he oedained to be proclaimed through the whole world, and reſolved to
                        take a journey himſelf to Conſtantinople, to cary the particulars.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
                    <ab>How king Pepin haſtends to Greece to bear theſe tidings; and how he found Conſtantinople beſieged by the ſoldan of Egypt.</ab>
                    <p>KING PEPIN departed into Greece and arrived at Rom, where the pope received him joyfully; but as he ſat at dinner, news was
                        brought that the ſoldan of Egypt had beſiwged Conſtantinople, whereupon he craved the aid of the pop, who readily granted it:
                        An army was immediately raiſed, and marched with king Pepin to Conſtantinople, where he found the city cloſely befirt with the
                        ſoldan's army; but when the emperor heard relief was come, he took courage. But<lb/><fw type="header" place="bottom"
                            ><!-- bad page --></fw><pb n="58"/><fw type="header" place="top">58 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>the ſoldan with high words
                        encountered them, not only to ſubdue Conſtantinople, but Rome itſelf. But king Pepin ſent letters to the emperor to make a
                        ſally when he gave the onſet.</p>
                    <p>The ſoldan put his men in order to diſcover the number of his enemies. The green knight, with the like intent, perceiving them
                        coming by the ſide of the hill, addreſſed himſelf to the encounter, broke his lance againſt the foremoſt; then began a
                        dreadful combat, and in the end he put him to flight. King Pepin upon this attacked the ſoldan's army with great fury; and
                        Mylan Douglar ſlew the king of Quile and three others.</p>
                    <p>This made the ſoldan and his men come up, and furiouſly ſet upon Douglar, and diſmounted him; had not the green knight reſcued
                        him, he had been ſlain.</p>
                    <p>The green knight, and other champions, made a terrible ſlaughter, ſo that the Saracens began to fly; but the king of Sclavonia,
                        coming with fifty thouſand freſh men, reſtored the battle, which continued bloody and doubtful. But king Pepin and the
                        emperor, finding they were over numbered, thought fit to retire into the city.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="59"/>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 59</fw>
                    <lb/>
                    <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine and Orſon arrived at the Caſtle, wherein Clerimond was; and how a brazen-head infromed them of their
                        parents.</ab>
                    <p>AFTER many days travel, at laſt Valentine and Orſon lighted upon an iſland, in which ſtood a caſtle covered with braſs, that
                        drove Valentine into ſuſpicion, that this was it whereunto the green knight had directed him, and approaching it, he demanded
                        who was the owner of the caſtle? Anſwer was returned, <hi><said>"That the fiar lady Clarimond, ſiſter to the giant Ferragus;
                                and built by a Saracen, and amongſt all others his excellent works, had placed great rarities in one particular
                                chamber of it."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>Amongſt many things it was alſo told unto Valentine, that in the chamber ſtood an excellent pillar, on which ſtood a head of
                        braſs, made by the art of necromancy, that gave anſwer to any thing that was demanded. Valentine hearing this ſtrange
                        relation, was perſiaded that this was the caſtle, wherein the green knight told him he ſhould find his ſiſter; ſo, without
                        delay, he and Orſon rid up to the gates, where <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">thinking</fw><pb n="60"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">60 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>thinking to enter, the were reſiſted by ten ſturdy knights that kept the gates.</p>
                    <p>When they ſaw Valentine and Orſon offer to enter, they ſaid unto them, <hi><said>"whatever you be withdraw yourſelvves back,
                                for none enters here without the leave of a maiden, to whom we belong."</said></hi>
                        <said>Why,</said> quoth Valentine, <hi><said>"go aſk her, whether it be her pleaſure we enter or not?"</said></hi> Hereupon on
                        of them went to Clarimond, and told her, <said>there were two knights that ſeem fierce and courageous,deſire to enter your
                            caſtle.— </said><hi><said>"Defend,</said> quoth ſhe, <said>while I go to a window to take a view of them, and let the
                                gates be ſurely kept."</said></hi> Then ſhe looked out of a window and ſaid, <hi><said>"what are you that dare offer
                                to enter my caſtle, without my leave?"</said></hi>
                        <said>Lady,</said> quoth Valentine, <said>I would be glad to ſpeak with that head of braſs which is within this caſtle, and,
                            as I underſtand, resolves doubts.——</said><hi><said>"Knight,</said> quoth ſhe, <said>if you have any certain token either
                                from king Perragus or the green knight you may enter, not otherwiſe, or try your fortune in ſingle combat with the
                                Senſchal of this place."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>This choice choſe Valentine, rather than bewray the rign which the green knight had given him to preſent to his ſiſter.——The
                        lady ſeeing his reſolute hardineſs, fell <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">in</fw><pb n="61"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                            >VALENTINE AND ORSON. 61</fw><lb/>in love with him, and preſently went into the chamber where the beazen-head ſtood, and
                        ſaying, <hi><said>what is that knight od courage, that would ſo gladly enter this caſtle?</said></hi> was anſwered, ſhe ſhould
                        not know until the knight was preſent. Clarimond, at this anſwer, ſeemed very ſorrowful, for ſhe was greatly in love with
                        Valentine.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine diſcover's Clarimond's love: How he jeſts with the Seneſchal, and overcomes him, and enters the caſtle by
                        force.</ab>
                    <p>CLERIMOND hereupon ſent for the Seneſchal, and told him, <hi><said>"that this knight would enter the caſtle by
                            force."</said></hi> The Seneſchal ſaid, <hi><said>lady, if he be ſo hardy, let him attempt it."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>So mounteing his horſe, the iſſued out of the gate, and the lady got into the window to ſee the combat, which was very fierce
                        and doubtful, until after three careers, in which Valentine had the better every tiem, he threw both horſe and man to the
                        earth. The Seneſchal finding himſelf in danger, ſaid to Valentine, <said>knight, I know not from <lb/><fw type="sig"
                                place="bottom">F</fw><lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">whence</fw><pb n="62"/><fw type="header" place="top">62 THE
                                HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>whence you are, but never in my lide, found I ſuch a man of valour, and withal I give thee leave
                            to enter this caſtle; but upon this condition, that you ſpeak not unto lady Clarimond.</said> Quoth Valentine, <said>I
                            will not depart hence, until I have ſpoken with her and the beazen-head.——</said>The lady all this while ſtanding at the
                        window, at laſt ſaid to one of her maids, <said>ſee how indiſcreet this Seneſchal is to dight with ſuch a caliant knight, who
                            long ſince might have taken away his life.</said> When Valentine ſaw the pride of the Seneſchal, and that he ſtood out
                        with him, being his priſoner, he preſently ran another courſe, and gave him ſo deadly a blow that he ran him quite through the
                        body, and he tumbled from his forſe to the ground, at which the lady Clerimond was exceedingly joyful, and commanded them to
                        ſet open the gates, and Valentine to be brought up unto her, and thus ſaid, <hi><said>ſir knight, you are welcome, for I never
                                ſaw a more valiant and courageous man enter my caſtle, for it appears by our valour, that you are deſended from ſome
                                royal blood."</said></hi></p>
                    <p><said>"Fair lady,</said> replies Valentine, <said>neither myſelf nor my companion ever knew of what extraction we are; he was
                            nourished by a beaſt in the foreſt, and lived there <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">like</fw><pb n="63"/><fw
                                type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 63</fw><lb/>like a wild man, until I conquered him by my ſword:
                            Wherefore lady, thus far have I travelled to get knowledge of my parents; but chiefly to gain the love of you being ſo
                            fair a lady."</said></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine ſhewed Clarimond the green knight's ring, which ſhe gave him, and how he queſtioned with the brazen-head
                        concerning his deſcent.</ab>
                    <p>VALENTINE hacing purchaſed his entrance, at laſt ſhewed the ring that the green knight had given him, upon which Clarimond told
                        him, <said>"that he need not have endangered himſelf ſo much to get acceſs in this caſtle, had he ſhewed that at
                            first."</said></p>
                    <p>When dinner was ended, ſhe took him by the hand, and led him to the chamber where the brazen head ſtood: Being come to the
                        door, they found it guarded on one ſide, by a <hi>grim, ugly</hi> ſhaped villain, with a club of iron on his neck, and on the
                        other ſide, ſtood a moſt fierce lion: Valentine perceiving them to make reſiſtance, demanded of Clarimond the meaning, who
                            <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">ſaid,</fw><pb n="64"/><fw type="header" place="top">64 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>ſaid,
                            <said>theſe are to keep the door, that none may enter without my knowledge.</said></p>
                    <p><said>Lady,</said> ſays Valentine, <said>I mean to try my fortune with the lions,</said> and by main ſtrength caught him about
                        the body, whereat the lion forſook him. Orſon too aſſailed the villain, and before he could lift up his club, he took him by
                        the middle ſo <hi>ſtrongly,</hi> that he threw him againſt the wall, took away his club, and <hi>gave</hi> him ſuch a blow,
                        that he tumbled him on the ground, and his it not been for the lady Vlarimond, he had ſlain him on the ſpot. Being thus both
                        canquished, they entered the chamber, wherein they <hi>might</hi> ſee rubies, diamonds, and a multitude of precious ſtones:
                        Within four pillars of jaſper, ſtood the beazen-head; Valentine fixed his eyes chiefly on the brazen-head, at length, when all
                        was ſilent, it began to ſpeak in this manner: <said>"Thou famous knight, of royal parentage, art called Valentine the valiant,
                            of whom it may be truly ſaid, there was never the like came before me. Thou art he who only deſerves the lady Clerimond,
                            thou art ſon to the emperor of Greece, and thy mother's name is Belliſant, ſiſter to king Pepin of France, who by wrong
                                <hi>ſuggeſtion,</hi> is baniſhed her coun<lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">try,</fw><pb n="65"/><fw type="header"
                                place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 65</fw><lb/>trym and huſband's bed; know this, thy mother is in Portugal, and in the
                            caſtle of Ferragus, who hath kept her thoſe twenty years. <hi>King Pepin</hi> of France is thy uncle, and the wild man who
                            accompanies thee is thy brother; you two were delivered by the empreſs Belliſant, in the foreſt of Orleans, and <hi>being
                                brought</hi> forth, thy champion was taken away by a ravenous bear, who nouriſhed him in the woods <hi>among</hi> her
                            whelps; for they part thou waſt found the very ſame day by <hi>king Pepin,</hi> who had nouriſhed thee ever ſince.
                            Moreover thy brother ſhall never have the use of his tongue until a thread be cut inder the ſame."</said></p>
                    <p>Valentine marking well what the head had declared, fell upon the boſom of his brother Orſon, and they embraced each other; and
                        alſo told the lady he would marry her on the condition ſhe would renounce Mahometaniſm, as her brother the <hi>green
                            knight</hi> had, to which ſhe anſwered, ſhe would be obedient in every reſpect during her life to his will.</p>
                    <p>Upon theſe tidings the joy of the inhabitants was very <hi>great</hi>; but all their <hi>gladneſs</hi> was ſuddenly eclipſed by
                        the treachery of her brother Ferragus, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewn.</p>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">F2</fw>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="66"/>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <fw type="header" place="top">66 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                    <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
                    <ab>How Pacolet the inchanter infromed the giant Ferragus of all that paſſed between Valentine and his ſiſter.</ab>
                    <p>NOW you ſhall underſtand, that within this caſtle where Clerimond was, dwelt a dwarf, whom ſhe had brought up from a child,
                        named Pacolet, being of more wit than ſtature, and who ahd by ſtudy got a great inſight into necromancy, by which art he
                        compoſed a little horſe of wood, in the head of which he had ſo artifically fixed a pin that every time he mounted him, he
                        would turn the pin towards the place he would go to, and ſuddenly he would be there withoug danger: This Pacolet, obſerving
                        what had paſſed in the caſtle, took his horſe and went to Portugal, and related the ſtory to Ferragus, which when Ferragus
                        heard, he was exceedingly angry, both againſt his ſiſter and Valentine; againſt her for marrying a chriſtian knight, and
                        againſt him for taking her to wife, ſwearing by the Gods to take revenge on them both.</p>
                    <p>But all this he diſſembled to Pacolet, bidding him bear this meſſage to Clari<lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">mond,</fw><pb
                            n="67"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 67</fw><lb/>mond, <said>that Valentine, who ſhall have her to
                            wife, is right welcome, and not long before I will come with my nobles, and then ſhall their nuptials be royally
                            ſolemnized;</said> ſo Pacolet mounted his horſe; was in an inſtant in the perſence of his lady, and told her what he had
                        done, and what her brother ſaid. At this the lady ſtood amazed, but at laſt anſwered him thus, <said>"I am angry thou didſt
                            not tell me of thy departure, for thou ſhouldſt have enquired for a chriſtain woman, one that has had her abiding in my
                            brother's caſtle."</said></p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
                    <ab>How Pacolet made a hourney into Portugal, to ſee the lady Belliſant, Valentine's mother.</ab>
                    <p>THE lady having ended her tale, Pacolet ſaid, <said>"lady, I ſhall for your ſake, make another journey into Portugal, and
                            before to-morrow night <hi>bring</hi> you <hi>tidings</hi>, whether ſhe be there or no;"</said> at this Valentine much
                        wondered, until the lady told him he could do it by his art. Then called Orſon to him, and cut the thread under his
                            <hi>tongue,</hi> which <hi>being</hi> done, <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">he</fw><pb n="68"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">68 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>he ſpoke perſently, and related the ſtory of his life; Pacolet, according to his
                        promiſe, performed his journey, and brought Valentine word. how he had ſeen his mother in <hi>good</hi> health, which made him
                            <hi>exceeding glad.</hi></p>
                    <p>But theſe joys laſted not <hi>long,</hi> for ſoon after arrived <hi>Ferragus</hi> at the caſtle of Clarimond, and Valentine
                        believing what <hi>he</hi> had ſpoken, ſaid, <said>"It is reported to me, that within your caſtle, for the ſpace of twenty
                            years you have maintained a chriſtain woman, who is mother under me, whom I would gladly ſee, her name is Belliſant,
                            ſiſter to <hi>king Pepin</hi> of France and wife to the emperor of Greece."——</said><said>By Mahomet,</said> ſaid
                            <hi>Ferragus</hi>, <said> you ſay true, and you ſhall <hi>go along</hi> with me into <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſo ſhall you be
                            informed, whether ſhe be the lady you ſeek after or no.</said>
                        <said>Gramercy,</said> quoth Valentine, and ſo Ferragus left him, and ſaid to Clarimond, <said>ſiſter, I deſire your
                            advancement more than any thing on earth; wherefore, to knit up all at once, my deſire is, that you would to with me into
                                <hi>Protugal,</hi> and there, with the conſent and applauſe of all my hobels, we intend <hi>hightly</hi> to ſolemnize
                            your nuptial day.</said></p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb n="69"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 69</fw>
                    <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine and Orſon were betrayed by Ferragus, and committed to priſon.</ab>
                    <p>SOON after this they all embarked;—but Ferragus fell from his former words of comfort, and began to plot the death of Valentine
                        and Orſon.——In the dead time of night he cauſed them to be bound in chains. Now when Clarimond ſaw what was done to her lover,
                        ſhe fell in extreme agony, and would have ſlain herſelf, or elſe violently have leaped overboard into the ſea.</p>
                    <p>Ferragus ſeeing her in this fit, gave command that ſhe ſhould be attended by ſome of his barons; and that ſhe ſhould not ſo
                        much as ſpeak to the priſoners. Thus were their joys ſuddenly blaſted; and all this while they were on their way towards
                        Portugal, and ſhortly after arrived at the caſtle of Ferragus.</p>
                    <p>They were no ſooner arrived, but Belliſant heard it, and that two chriſtain knights were brought priſoners to the caſtle. She
                        had a great deſire to ſee them, but Ferragus oppoſed it, and commanded the goaler to commit them to the dungeon, <lb/><fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">to</fw><pb n="70"/><fw type="header" place="top">70 THE HISTORY OF</fw><lb/>to live on bread
                        and water, and be laſhed twice a day, or change their religion.</p>
                    <p>After Ferragus had committed them, he called for his ſiſter Clarimond, and reproved her ſharply, for lamenting the knights that
                        had been the overthrow of her brother, the green knight, and who were of a faith contrary to her's: but this only ſerved to
                        increaſe her ſorrow, which being obſerved by Belliſant to be immoderate, ſhe aſked the reaſon; when ſhe told her, that the two
                        knights, priſoners, were her children; but now Ferragus betrayed them, under the pretence of renouncing his faith.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP XX.</head>
                    <ab>How Pacolet releaſed Valentine and Orſon out of priſon, with their mother and fair Clarimond.</ab>
                    <p>FERRAGUS made a great feaſt among his nobles; they paſſed the day in ſuch revelling and mirth, that the night growing late they
                        betook themſelves to reſt.—Pacolet was ſtill upon the watch to perform his promiſe; and coming to the door of the <lb/><fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">dungeon</fw><pb n="71"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 71</fw><lb/>dungeon
                        where the lady's two ſons lady bound, as ſoon as he touched the door, the locks broke and flew open. The two princes hearing
                        the door open, expected it to be the <hi>goaler</hi> come to kill them; but Pacolet ſoon eaſed them of their fears, ſaying,
                            <said>Follow me, and before to-morrow's ſun I ſhall bring you both unto your mother.</said> Great was the joy of theſe two
                        renowned preſons.</p>
                    <p>After this Pacolet led them to the chamber where the two ladies ſat mourning. Orſon deſired Pacolet to open the foor where
                        Ferragus lay, that he might ſlay him; but Clarimond perſuaded him to the contrary, telling him, <said>that id he ſhould murder
                            him, we ſhould loſe the love of my brother, the <hi>green knight.</hi></said></p>
                    <p>At his very time, Pacolet, by his art, had opened the gates of the caſtle, and they followed him down to one of the ports where
                        he had provided a ſhip, and having a fair gale, they ſpeedily arrived at the caſtle of Clarimond; whither being come they
                        refreſhed themſelves with pleaſure.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <pb n="72"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">72 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                    <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
                    <ab>How Ferragus aſſembles a mighty army, and ſails to Aquitain to revenge himſelf of Valentine and his ſiſter Clarimond.</ab>
                    <p>FERRAGUS got ready a great fleet, and ſcoured the ſeas to take Valentine, was forced, after a fruitleſs ſearch, to return hom
                        to his palace, whilſt Valentine's company arrived at Aquitain, and not caring to diſcover themſelves to the duke Savory,
                        lodged themſelves in a private houſe; for Orſon, knowing the inconſtancy of the fair ſex, had a mind to try the lady Fexon,
                        ere he married her; and therefore, taking the habit of a knight-errand, and making Pacolet his page, he entered the hall of
                        duke Savory's palace, and aſked whether he would take him in ſervice? To which the duke anſwered, not knowing Orſon, that he
                        would accept of it very willingly, and would reward him liberally; therefore preſented him with a purſe of money, and withal
                        made him a champion of the court.</p>
                    <p>Orſon ſoon, by his courteous behaviour, got the love of every body, and was much reſpected by the lady Fezon, who did not
                            <lb/><fw type="catch" place="bottom">know</fw><pb n="73"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON.
                        73</fw><lb/>know him to be Orſon, becauſe of his ſpeech. Of theſe paſſages, Orſon, at convenient times, would acquaint
                        Valentine, Clarimond, and his mother Belliſant, who were greatly rejoiced therewith, but this joy was interrupted by
                        Ferragus's proclaiming war againſt the duke of Aquitain.</p>
                    <p>Ferragus ſoon arrived with a great army, and duke Savory prepared to receive him, and raiſed ſiege with all his armed men,
                        among whom were Valentine, Orſon, and Pacolet, unkown to the duke.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
                    <ab>How the duke was taken priſoner in the battle, and how by the help of Pacolet, Orſon ſet him free.</ab>
                    <p>DUKE SAVORY began the battle with great fierceneſs the next morning, which proved very bloody; in which, adventuring too far,
                        he was ſurrounded by Ferragus's men, which ſtruck ſuch amazement to the chriſtians, that they would have forſaken the field,
                        until Valentine and Orſon ſeeing them thus to waver, came up to them with all ſpeed, and cried to them, <said>"ſhew yourſelves
                            men; run not away in the time of extremity."</said></p>
                    <fw type="sig" place="bottom">G</fw>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Theſe</fw>
                    <pb n="74"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">74 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                    <p>Theſe two knight having thus done ſpeaking, the people began to gather up their forces, and began to fight anew.—Valentine was
                        the thickeſt, hewing forth his way with his ſword, whilſt Orſon on the other hand, was not idle, who had ſworn to free the
                        duke from captivity, or leave his body among the reſt. Pacolet, the magician, promiſed Orſon his aſſiſtance; upon which he put
                        ſpurs to his horſe, and ran violently though the hotteſt and the thickeſt of the battle, and being paſt danger, threw away his
                        own ſheild, and hung about his neck the ſhield of a Saracen, paſt through the thickeſt whithout oppoſition, and came to the
                        pavilion, where the duke was priſoner, but Pacolet perceiving the guards to be numerous, by his art, he caſt them into a
                        deadly ſleep, and approaching the duke, Orſon ſaid, <said>mount this horſe, I came to free thee from Ferragus; if thou doubt
                            what I am, I am the knight in your hall demanded wages of you.</said>
                        <said>Knight,</said> quoth the duke, <said>for this ſervice I will give you my daughter Fezon in marriage: Indeed, I have
                            promiſed her to another knight, but he was wild and ſavage, and had not the uſe of his tongue; but by his long abſence, I
                            fear he has won ſome other lady.</said> This ſaid, they all took their way through the enemy's camp.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">Valentine,</fw>
                    <pb n="75"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 75</fw>
                    <p>Valentine, all this while, was demanding what was become of his brother Orſon, but found none to give any tidings of him; and
                        ruſhing through the thickeſt and hotteſt of the fight, at lengh loſt his horſe: Ferragus ſeeing him ſo valiant a knight,
                        ſeized him on as a priſoner, bound him hand and foot, and ſo carried him to his pavilion.</p>
                    <p>Orſon, Pacolet, and the duke returning, ſet upon him. Orſon crying out, <said>let him not eſcape us;</said> and therewith ſet
                        ſpurs to his horſe, and ran ſo fiercely againſt Ferragus, that both he and Valentine fell to the earth, and by this means was
                        releaſed, and mounted on a freſh horſe, and ſo returned to thier friends.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
