<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Archive of Digital Editions of Valentine and Orson</title>
                <sponsor>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </funder>
                <editor>
                    <name>Anna Kroon</name>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Anna Kroon</persName>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- editionStmt is optional, but recommended by TEI-C guidelines if in case of multiple editions. It is used to group information on a single edition of text -->
                <edition>Edition statement...</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <!-- publicationStmt is mandatory. It groups information concerning the publication or distribution of the digital TEI object; use <sourceDesc> section below to record publication data that may be different than TEI edition, say for an historical source work.  -->
                <publisher><!-- the person or ogranization responsible for the creation of TEI edition, and who has rights over its production and/or distribution -->Publisher
                    Name</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><!-- repeat addrLine as needed -->Address Line 1,</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <!-- availability statement clarifies a general copyright and fair use policy governing reuse of the TEI edition -->
                    <licence target="URL_of_full_license"> Summary statement of which license applies to this TEI file </licence>
                    <p><!-- okay to add <p> to include other related but necessary blocks of information -->Availablity statement continued...</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2017-01-01"><!-- the date of publication of the TEI edition -->Publication Date</date>
                <distributor><!-- you can identify organization responsible for the distribution or purchase handling of the TEI edition -->Distributor
                    of this TEI Edition</distributor>
                <date><!-- provide a date for update on availability statement if different than publication date -->Availability Date</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--  <seriesStmt>
                seriesStmt is optional. It records the relation between separate documents understood as each part of a series (e.g., collected works (essays, lectures, articles, etc.), document volumes, etc.) by declaring its parent work/identity 
                <title level="s">Title of Series</title>
                <respStmt>
                    name of person responsible for series, e.g., editor or organization 
                    <resp>ed. by...</resp>
                    <name>Name of Editor</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope unit="vol">biblScope...</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">idno...</idno>
            </seriesStmt> -->

            <notesStmt>
                <!-- notesStmt is optional. It adds multiple notes for additional information or discussion of document -->
                <note><!-- repeat <note> as needed -->Notes on the text...</note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc is mandatory. It describes the source from which an electronic text was derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description <bibl> in the case of a digitized edition of a print text; in the case where the TEI file is born digital,we can include <p>"born digital"</p> -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>The renowned history of Valentine and Orson, the two sons of the Emperor of Greece</title>
                    <pubPlace>Haverhill</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Peter Edes</publisher>
                    <date>1794</date></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- encodingDesc section is optional, but recommended. It groups elements for recording information on the encoding practices used in relation to source work's orginal formatting; this section can range from a brief statement on encoding approach under <projectDesc> to a more detailed overview of editorial decisions under <editorialDesc> -->
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- a statment on purpose of TEI edition, project objectives, teams, etc -->
                <p>A Project Description ...</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <!-- can use this section to provide details on how text(s) at project level were selected -->
                <p> Information about text(s) in collection </p>
            </samplingDecl>

            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <!-- one might wish to note any "corrections" or alterations -->
                    <p>A Correction statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <!-- we can also record any regularization decisions made to source work in translating into a digital format -->
                    <p>A Normalization statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition for reasons of regularizing the work for digital
                        format</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p> Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation marks, etc.) </p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>This edition only retains hyphenation between words that would exist regardless of line breaks. Line break or page break
                        hyphenation has not be retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p> Information about any interpretive information added to the text </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- Inside cover has writing on it. To encode or not to encode? -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- more handwriting -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- empty page -->
            <pb/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE <lb/>RENOWNED <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON,</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="sub">THE TWO SONS <lb/>OF THE <lb/>EMPEROR OF GREECE.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>HAVERHILL,</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>PRINTED BY <name>PETER EDES.</name></publisher>
                    <docDate>MDCCXCIV.</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="book">
                <head>The <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON.</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                    <ab>How King Pepin baniſhed his Queen Bertha, and how he gave his ſiſter Belliſant, in marriage to Alexander, emperor of
                        Conſtantinople.</ab>
                    <p>WE find it ſet down in ancient Chronicale, that the thrice noble and valiant Pepin, king of France, took to wife Bertha, who
                        was deſended of royal race. This lady was very fair and wiſe, but much incumbered with troubles, which with great patience ſhe
                        ſuffered. The chief inſtrument of all the miſchief towards this good queen, was plotted by a falſe old woman who firſt brought
                        her in <fw type="catch" place="bottom">diſgrace</fw>
                        <pb n="4"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">4 THE HISTORY OF</fw> diſgrace with the king her huſband, and after to be baniſhed his bed,
                        while ſhe in a cunning manner brought in her daughter in the queen's ſtead. This old woman having brought her treachery to
                        effect, for (her daughter was very like Bertha) it forcame to paſs, that king Pepin had two ſons by this maiden, viz. Haufrey
                        and Henry, both which ſons ſo grieved the king, and waſted the country of France by thier outrages and fury, that they cauſed
                        the queen to be utterly baniſhed; by which ſhe endured many ſorrowful days; but at laſt ſhe began to recieve confort again,
                        for ſo it happened, that at the requeſt of divers lords of France, this good queen began to fing favor with the king her
                        huſband, who when he knew the treachery of that wicked woman againſt her, he much bewailed the miſery ſhe had endured, and
                        recieved her again with great honor and triumph. The queen reſtored to her former bed, conceived and bore the king a ſon,
                        called Charlemain the Puiſſant.</p>
                    <p>This king Pepin had a ſiſter named Belliſant, a woman of great wit and beauty. It chanced ſo that the fam of this lovely
                        perſonage ſpread abroad, that at laſt Alexander, emperor of Conſtantinople, came <fw type="catch" place="bottom">into</fw><pb
                            n="5"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 5</fw> into France, accompanied with a gallant troop of his
                        nobility. This emperor after his arrival, ſuddenly aſſembled all his lords, in their rich habiliments, appointing them to take
                        their way towards king Pepin's court. King Pepin underſtanding this ſudeen but joygul news, made great preparations for
                        entertaining this emperor. King Pepin, with all his noble train, went to meet the emperor, with great joy, and conducted him
                        to the court of France, where fair Belliſant was, and ſhe entertained him with no leſs joy than her brother had done
                        before.</p>
                    <p>This marriage being known among all the inhabitants, there was great joy on every ſide. When the time appointed came, theſe two
                        were eſpouſed in all honor fitting for their eſtates. This marriage feaſt held long, btu being ended, the emperor preprared to
                        take his leave of his new brother-in-law, and take his way towards Conſtantinople, with his fiar empreſs Beliſant. Theſe
                        mighty princes name near a port of the ſea, where they were obliged to take leave of each other, which they done with ſuch
                        tenderneſs, as I am not able to ecpreſs, giving his ſiſter many rich gifts, and then embraced her, with <fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">A2</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">weeping</fw><pb n="6"/><fw type="header" place="top">6 THE HISTORY
                            OF</fw> weeping eyes he left her to the mercy of the waves. Then all the lords and ladies took their leave of each other.
                        The emperor and all his train arrived ſafe at Conſtantinople; at their landing, they were all recieved with great joy and
                        triumph. But mark what happened to the poor lady Belliſant, who by treaſon and falſe accuſations, was caſt out and
                        baniſhed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                    <ab>How the arch prieſt of Conſtantinople betrayed the emperor, by making love to fiar Belliſant the empreſs; and how the arch
                        prieſt, recieving a repulſe from Belliſant, practiſed treaſon againſt her.</ab>
                    <p>IN Conſtantinople lived and arch prieſt, in whom the emperor put great truſt, and committed to hom all his boſom ſecrets, and
                        made him governor over all his houſe; as alſo he was principal confeſſor, and one of his greateſt gavorites. The prieſt,
                        forgetting all the emperor's favors, and being overcome with the beauty<fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw><pb n="7"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 7</fw> of the new empreſs, inordinate luſt ſo far prevailed with him, that
                        one time ſpying her alone ſitting ſolitary in her chamber, he went in and ſat down by her. At firſt he began to behold her
                        with a ſmiling countenance, of all which the lady miſtruſted nothing, neither had ſhe any evil thought of him. But at laſt,
                        after many jeſtures of impurity, he begain to utter his laſcivious thoughts in a preſſing and amorous manner.</p>
                    <p>His ſpeeches being ended, the lady, out of a grave and prudent carriage, made an excellent anſwer to this wicked preiſt.—
                            <said>Thou falſe, unjuſt, and deviliſh prieſt! ſtain to thy profeſſion! how dareſt thou open thy mouth to ſuch a maſs of
                            cillanies as many thereon enſue? Firſt, as I may ſay, againſt the ſacred order; and ſecondly againſt the majeſty of that
                            emperor that ever nouriſhed thee, and hath raiſed thee to great ginities, and from whom may juſtly proceed the ſentence of
                            condemnation, both on thee and me, if he but knew thy laſacivious and wicked practices? Let gall, I ſay theſe vile
                            provocations to luſt, and leave for ever hereafter to ſolicit me in this manner; which if thou proſecuteſt any further,
                            thou canſt ex<fw type="catch" place="bottom">pect</fw><pb n="8"/><fw type="header" place="top">8 THE HISTORY OF</fw>pect
                            nothing but a ſhamefil downfall, and a moſt damnable death. Therefore depart, and ſee that you tempt me no
                        more.</said></p>
                    <p>This angry farewel of the worthy empreſs, ſtung the prieſt to the very heart, but he durſt make no reply, but craved pardon for
                        his bold and raſh follies comitted. This being ſore troubled in mind, he reſolved ſeveral days what to do againſt this
                        innocent lady.</p>
                </div>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
