<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Archive of Digital Editions of Valentine and Orson</title>
                <sponsor>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </sponsor>
                <funder>
                    <name>University of New Haven Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship</name>
                </funder>
                <editor>
                    <name>Anna Kroon</name>
                </editor>
                <principal>
                    <persName>Anna Kroon</persName>
                </principal>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- editionStmt is optional, but recommended by TEI-C guidelines if in case of multiple editions. It is used to group information on a single edition of text -->
                <edition>Edition statement...</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <!-- publicationStmt is mandatory. It groups information concerning the publication or distribution of the digital TEI object; use <sourceDesc> section below to record publication data that may be different than TEI edition, say for an historical source work.  -->
                <publisher><!-- the person or ogranization responsible for the creation of TEI edition, and who has rights over its production and/or distribution -->Publisher
                    Name</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><!-- repeat addrLine as needed -->Address Line 1,</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <!-- availability statement clarifies a general copyright and fair use policy governing reuse of the TEI edition -->
                    <licence target="URL_of_full_license"> Summary statement of which license applies to this TEI file </licence>
                    <p><!-- okay to add <p> to include other related but necessary blocks of information -->Availablity statement continued...</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2017-01-01"><!-- the date of publication of the TEI edition -->Publication Date</date>
                <distributor><!-- you can identify organization responsible for the distribution or purchase handling of the TEI edition -->Distributor
                    of this TEI Edition</distributor>
                <date><!-- provide a date for update on availability statement if different than publication date -->Availability Date</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--  <seriesStmt>
                seriesStmt is optional. It records the relation between separate documents understood as each part of a series (e.g., collected works (essays, lectures, articles, etc.), document volumes, etc.) by declaring its parent work/identity 
                <title level="s">Title of Series</title>
                <respStmt>
                    name of person responsible for series, e.g., editor or organization 
                    <resp>ed. by...</resp>
                    <name>Name of Editor</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope unit="vol">biblScope...</biblScope>
                <idno type="ISSN">idno...</idno>
            </seriesStmt> -->

            <notesStmt>
                <!-- notesStmt is optional. It adds multiple notes for additional information or discussion of document -->
                <note><!-- repeat <note> as needed -->Notes on the text...</note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <!-- sourceDesc is mandatory. It describes the source from which an electronic text was derived or generated, typically a bibliographic description <bibl> in the case of a digitized edition of a print text; in the case where the TEI file is born digital,we can include <p>"born digital"</p> -->
                <bibl>
                    <title>The renowned history of Valentine and Orson, the two sons of the Emperor of Greece</title>
                    <pubPlace>Haverhill</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>Peter Edes</publisher>
                    <date>1794</date></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <!-- encodingDesc section is optional, but recommended. It groups elements for recording information on the encoding practices used in relation to source work's orginal formatting; this section can range from a brief statement on encoding approach under <projectDesc> to a more detailed overview of editorial decisions under <editorialDesc> -->
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- a statment on purpose of TEI edition, project objectives, teams, etc -->
                <p>A Project Description ...</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <!-- can use this section to provide details on how text(s) at project level were selected -->
                <p> Information about text(s) in collection </p>
            </samplingDecl>

            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <!-- one might wish to note any "corrections" or alterations -->
                    <p>A Correction statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <!-- we can also record any regularization decisions made to source work in translating into a digital format -->
                    <p>A Normalization statement on any edits made of source work in TEI edition for reasons of regularizing the work for digital
                        format</p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p> Information about treatment of quotations (preservation of original quotation marks, etc.) </p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>This edition only retains hyphenation between words that would exist regardless of line breaks. Line break or page break
                        hyphenation has not be retained.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <interpretation>
                    <p> Information about any interpretive information added to the text </p>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- Inside cover has writing on it. To encode or not to encode? -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- more handwriting -->
            <pb/>
            <!-- empty page -->
            <pb/>
            <titlePage>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">THE <lb/>RENOWNED <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON,</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="sub">THE TWO SONS <lb/>OF THE <lb/>EMPEROR OF GREECE.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <docImprint>
                    <pubPlace>HAVERHILL,</pubPlace>
                    <publisher>PRINTED BY <name>PETER EDES.</name></publisher>
                    <docDate>MDCCXCIV.</docDate>
                </docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="book">
                <head>The <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/>VALENTINE AND ORSON.</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. I.</head>
                    <ab>How King Pepin baniſhed his Queen Bertha, and how he gave his ſiſter Belliſant, in marriage to Alexander, emperor of
                        Conſtantinople.</ab>
                    <p>WE find it ſet down in ancient Chronicale, that the thrice noble and valiant Pepin, king of France, took to wife Bertha, who
                        was deſended of royal race. This lady was very fair and wiſe, but much incumbered with troubles, which with great patience ſhe
                        ſuffered. The chief inſtrument of all the miſchief towards this good queen, was plotted by a falſe old woman who firſt brought
                        her in <fw type="catch" place="bottom">diſgrace</fw>
                        <pb n="4"/>
                        <fw type="header" place="top">4 THE HISTORY OF</fw> diſgrace with the king her huſband, and after to be baniſhed his bed,
                        while ſhe in a cunning manner brought in her daughter in the queen's ſtead. This old woman having brought her treachery to
                        effect, for (her daughter was very like Bertha) it forcame to paſs, that king Pepin had two ſons by this maiden, viz. Haufrey
                        and Henry, both which ſons ſo grieved the king, and waſted the country of France by thier outrages and fury, that they cauſed
                        the queen to be utterly baniſhed; by which ſhe endured many ſorrowful days; but at laſt ſhe began to recieve confort again,
                        for ſo it happened, that at the requeſt of divers lords of France, this good queen began to fing favor with the king her
                        huſband, who when he knew the treachery of that wicked woman againſt her, he much bewailed the miſery ſhe had endured, and
                        recieved her again with great honor and triumph. The queen reſtored to her former bed, conceived and bore the king a ſon,
                        called Charlemain the Puiſſant.</p>
                    <p>This king Pepin had a ſiſter named Belliſant, a woman of great wit and beauty. It chanced ſo that the fam of this lovely
                        perſonage ſpread abroad, that at laſt Alexander, emperor of Conſtantinople, came <fw type="catch" place="bottom">into</fw><pb
                            n="5"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 5</fw> into France, accompanied with a gallant troop of his
                        nobility. This emperor after his arrival, ſuddenly aſſembled all his lords, in their rich habiliments, appointing them to take
                        their way towards king Pepin's court. King Pepin underſtanding this ſudeen but joygul news, made great preparations for
                        entertaining this emperor. King Pepin, with all his noble train, went to meet the emperor, with great joy, and conducted him
                        to the court of France, where fair Belliſant was, and ſhe entertained him with no leſs joy than her brother had done
                        before.</p>
                    <p>This marriage being known among all the inhabitants, there was great joy on every ſide. When the time appointed came, theſe two
                        were eſpouſed in all honor fitting for their eſtates. This marriage feaſt held long, btu being ended, the emperor preprared to
                        take his leave of his new brother-in-law, and take his way towards Conſtantinople, with his fiar empreſs Beliſant. Theſe
                        mighty princes name near a port of the ſea, where they were obliged to take leave of each other, which they done with ſuch
                        tenderneſs, as I am not able to ecpreſs, giving his ſiſter many rich gifts, and then embraced her, with <fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">A2</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">weeping</fw><pb n="6"/><fw type="header" place="top">6 THE HISTORY
                            OF</fw> weeping eyes he left her to the mercy of the waves. Then all the lords and ladies took their leave of each other.
                        The emperor and all his train arrived ſafe at Conſtantinople; at their landing, they were all recieved with great joy and
                        triumph. But mark what happened to the poor lady Belliſant, who by treaſon and falſe accuſations, was caſt out and
                        baniſhed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. II.</head>
                    <ab>How the arch prieſt of Conſtantinople betrayed the emperor, by making love to fiar Belliſant the empreſs; and how the arch
                        prieſt, recieving a repulſe from Belliſant, practiſed treaſon againſt her.</ab>
                    <p>IN Conſtantinople lived and arch prieſt, in whom the emperor put great truſt, and committed to hom all his boſom ſecrets, and
                        made him governor over all his houſe; as alſo he was principal confeſſor, and one of his greateſt gavorites. The prieſt,
                        forgetting all the emperor's favors, and being overcome with the beauty<fw type="catch" place="bottom">of</fw><pb n="7"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 7</fw> of the new empreſs, inordinate luſt ſo far prevailed with him, that
                        one time ſpying her alone ſitting ſolitary in her chamber, he went in and ſat down by her. At firſt he began to behold her
                        with a ſmiling countenance, of all which the lady miſtruſted nothing, neither had ſhe any evil thought of him. But at laſt,
                        after many jeſtures of impurity, he begain to utter his laſcivious thoughts in a preſſing and amorous manner.</p>
                    <p>His ſpeeches being ended, the lady, out of a grave and prudent carriage, made an excellent anſwer to this wicked preiſt.—
                            <said>Thou falſe, unjuſt, and deviliſh prieſt! ſtain to thy profeſſion! how dareſt thou open thy mouth to ſuch a maſs of
                            cillanies as many thereon enſue? Firſt, as I may ſay, againſt the ſacred order; and ſecondly againſt the majeſty of that
                            emperor that ever nouriſhed thee, and hath raiſed thee to great ginities, and from whom may juſtly proceed the ſentence of
                            condemnation, both on thee and me, if he but knew thy laſacivious and wicked practices? Let gall, I ſay theſe vile
                            provocations to luſt, and leave for ever hereafter to ſolicit me in this manner; which if thou proſecuteſt any further,
                            thou canſt ex<fw type="catch" place="bottom">pect</fw><pb n="8"/><fw type="header" place="top">8 THE HISTORY OF</fw>pect
                            nothing but a ſhamefil downfall, and a moſt damnable death. Therefore depart, and ſee that you tempt me no
                        more.</said></p>
                    <p>This angry farewel of the worthy empreſs, ſtung the prieſt to the very heart, but he durſt make no reply, but craved pardon for
                        his bold and raſh follies comitted. This being ſore troubled in mind, he reſolved ſeveral days what to do againſt this
                        innocent lady.And feeling the emperor knew nothing of this matter from the empreſs, Belliſant, how the arch prieſt would have
                        enticed her to diſlotalty to him, but could not; therefore he began to accuſe her to the emperor for divers crimes. The arch
                        prieſt having now began to ſet abroach his deviliſh practices, he at laſt resolved that he would, under the cloak of
                        diſſimulation, make known his watchful care of his eſtate, welfare, and perſon. It fell out on a day when he ſpied the emperor
                        alone, he began to break out in this manner:</p>
                    <p><said>O emperor! thus it is, Belliſant, your wife, and ſiſter to the king of France, ſhe whom you advanced to this ſtate of
                            dignity, failed in the duty and loyalty which ſhe owes to her dread lord; for ſhe wandereth in her love, giving that to
                                another<fw type="catch" place="bottom">which</fw><pb n="9"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON 9</fw>
                            which is proper only to yourſelf. To name the perſon to your majeſty, I will not, for you know I am a ſacred prieſt, and
                            may not ſpill the blood of any man; but know for certain, that by the way of confeſſion I came to the light thereof,
                            whereof I neither ought nor will betray the name of him that thus betrays your bed; and what is worſe, ſhe daily deſires
                            your death, which grieves my heart to think on.</said></p>
                    <p>The emperor having heard this accuſation, little miſtrusſted the treachery of this arch prieſt, and gave credit to all his fair
                        but falſe words, and therewith became extreme penſive, that his truſt in her beauteous love had been thud decieved.</p>
                    <p>Upon a day entering into the chamber of his fair Brlliſant, without ſpeaking to her at all, in a fierce manner, her took her by
                        the hair of the head and dragged her about the chamber in a moſt inhuman manner, ſo the blood beſmeared her face. <said>Alas,
                            my lord,</said> ſad ſhe, <said>what moves you to this great outrage? I call the Gods to witneſs I never did any thing in
                            my life againſt your honor, or ever proſtituted my body to any ſtranger's love.</said> The emperor not being thus
                        ſatisfied, ſaid <said>thou<fw type="catch" place="bottom">whore!</fw><pb n="10"/><fw type="header" place="top">10 THE HISTORY
                                OF</fw> whore! I am too well informed of thy proceedings; and curſed be the day that I ſaw thy falſe, deceitful
                            face;</said> and with that daſhed her head againſt the ground, inſomuch, that all the damſels, her attendants, thought ſhe
                        had been dead.</p>
                    <p>The court being in an uproar upon this, up roſe a juſt, wiſe, courageous, and bold barron, and ſpoke to the emperor in this
                        manner: <said>Right worrthy ſir, I could wiſh you to be well adviſed; this lady id your eſpouſed wife, ſiſter to the great
                            king Pepin of France, whom when he ſhall hear of the great injury done to her, will muſter up all his men of war, and
                            ſuddenly ſurpriſe all our towns, wives, and children, and revenge upon us theſe cruel deeds unto his ſiſter.</said> The
                        worthy baron having thus ended his advice, the lady fell upon her knees before the emperor, and in tears thus ſhe ſpake.
                            <said>Alas, my lord, take pity on an innocent lady, for I am ſo free from any evil againſt your perſon or dignity. A
                            leaſt, my lord, poty the fruit of my body, for I am great with child by you. If nothing can appeaſe your anger to me, then
                            let my body be impriſoned in ſome ſtrong tower, until the time of my delive<fw type="catch" place="bottom">ry,</fw><pb
                                n="11"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 11</fw>ry, and then do with my body what pleaſeth you; ſo
                            the fruit of my body be kept ſafe.</said> The courtiers percieving nothing could mitigate the rage of the emperor, by a
                        common conſent removed her out of his preſence into another chamber. Having thus conveyed her away, the ladies that were her
                        attendants, fetched water to waſh her face, and did all they could to comfort her.</p>
                    <p>By this time the emperor's choler was a little pacified, by means of his lords and barons that attended him; inſomuch that he
                        cauſed Belliſant to be brought before him. When ſhe was come, his heart trembled and fretted for anger that he durſt not put
                        her to death, for fear of her mighty and puiſſant brother, king Pepin. <said>Thou curſed woman,</said> ſaid he, <said>were it
                            not for thy brother's ſake, the valiant Pepin of France, I would make thee fry in the fire as an example to all falſe
                            ladies.— Hear thy judgement. Now I baniſh thee out of my empire, and command that tomorrow thou depart out of this
                            city.</said></p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="12"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">12 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. III.</head>
                    <ab>How the traitorous arch prieſt put on the habit of a kinght at arms, and being well mounted, followed the empreſs Belliſant,
                        who was lately baniſhed. How Belliſant in her baniſhment was delivered of two ſons in the wood, whoſe names were Valentine and
                        Orſon; and how ſhe loſt them.</ab>
                    <p>THE arch prieſt, having wrought the baniſhment of fair Belliſant, began to think how he ſhould ſurely accompliſh his deſire,
                        wherefore he changed his white rocket into a coat of ſteel and a ſword: and being thus accoutred, he mounted a milk-white
                        ſteed, and made after her with greateſt expedition, enquiring of all he met which way the lady Belliſant was gone. After ſome
                        hours riding he came to a ſpaious foreſt, taking the direct way towards the lady. It chanced as he caſt his eye aſide, he
                        ſpied the lady ith her ſervant, Blandiman, ſitting by a fountain, lamenting her miſerable fortune; Blandiman uſing all the
                        means he could to comfort her.—The falſe prieſt ſoon percieved it to be the lady; but, by reaſon of his <fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">diſguiſe,</fw><pb n="13"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 13</fw>diſguiſe, ſhe could not
                        imagine him to be the arch prieſt, her enemy, but coming nearer, ſhe quickly knew him, and being ſtruck with ſudden fear, ſaid
                        to her ſervant, <said>alas! I well percieve this to be the arch prieſt, coming toward us, and I am fearful left he comes to do
                            me farther villainy.</said>
                        <said>Lday,</said> ſaid Blandiman, <said>if her comes to do you further harm, I'll encounter him body for body.</said> The
                        arch prieſt was ready to alight from his horſe, to ſalute the lady; and after he had made himdſelf known to her, he ſaid to
                        her in this manner:</p>
                    <p><said>Dear lady, the caſe is ſo pitiful, as to ſuffer baniſhment by ſentence even againſt thee by the emperor; if thou wilth
                            give me entertainment in thy love, I will bring to paſd, that the emperor ſhall recal thy baniſhment, and make thee ſhine
                            more bright than before.</said>
                        <said>Ah!</said> quoth the lady, <said>thou diſloyal and traitorous adverſary, I have no cause to beſtow love where my life
                            hath been put in jeopardy.</said> Quoth he, <said>utter not ſuch expreſſions againſt me, for I am not come to vex or
                            trouble you.</said> And in ſpeaking theſe words, he bent his body to the lady, thinking to have kiſſed her, but Blandiman
                        perceiving his intent, got between them, and gave the arch prieſt <fw type="sig" place="bottom">B</fw><fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">ſuch</fw><pb n="14"/><fw type="header" place="top">14 THE HISTORY OF </fw>ſuch s ſtroke as felled him to
                        the earth. The arch priest has no ſooner recovered himſelf, but preſently ſiezed his ſword, which Blandiman perceiving, took a
                        glabe which he had about him; whereupon grew a fore fight between them: This encounter laſted ſo long that they were both
                        wounded; but at laſt a merchant came by, who percieving that fierce encounter, cried out, <said>lords, leave off, and tell me
                            the cauſe of your variance, and I'll endeavor to end this controverſy.</said>
                        <said>Sir,</said> quoth Blandiman, <said>let us firſt try our right by weapons, and then we will be ruled by words.</said> But
                        the poor lady could no longer bear ſilence, but ſaid to the merchant, <said>alas! this man which you ſee armed, is the falſe
                            and traitorous arch prieſt that hath followed me to rob me of my honor, and force me to inſatiable luſt; alſo this is he
                            that hath made a ſeparation between me and the emperor, my lord and huſband.</said></p>
                    <p>The merchant hearing her lamentable tale, ſaid to the arch prieſt, <said>ſir, prieſt, leave off your enterpriſe, dare not ſo
                            much as touch this innocent lady; for if the emperor underſtood this villainy, he would ſoon end they life of
                            infamy.</said> As ſoon as <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw><pb n="15"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND
                            ORSON. 15</fw>the arch prieſt heard this, he forſook his company and feld through the wood.—— But his villanies were
                        afterwards diſcloſed. The merchant ſtaid ſome little time, bewailing the hard hap of the lady, yet comforted her, ſaying,
                            <said>alas! lady, I ſee that this arch prieſt has betrayed you, and brought you in hatred with the emperor; but I'll
                            promiſe you that, if I live, I'll declare all thoſe treacheries to the emperor; and bring the traitor to aſhameful
                            death.</said> So with many thanks for his aid from Blandiman, the merchant departed. THe merchant hacing left them,
                        Blandiman ſet the lady upon her horſe, and himſelf on his, ſo riding on, they came to a lodging in thier way, where they
                        remained eight days, during which time her ſervant was recovered of his wounds, and then ſet forward towards France, paſſing
                        by Orleans, they took their way towards Paris, where king Peping was uſed to ſojourn.</p>
                    <p>Belliſant (as aforeſaid) being with child, was ſuddenly overtaken in the foreſt; the time of her delivery being come, ſhe
                        forſook her horſe, and bid her ſervant lay her ſoftly under a green tree that grew hard by, and make haſte to get her the help
                        of a woman, <said>for I can go no farther, </said><fw type="catch" place="bottom">ſaid</fw><pb n="16"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">16 THE HISTORY OF</fw>ſaid ſhe, <said>my pains ſo increaſe upon me.</said> Blandiman obeyed her commands, and
                        left he ſhould not find the place again, ſet a mark, that he might the readier come thither again, ſo away he went to ſeek
                        ſome woman to help his diſtreſſed lady. He being gone, the lady was left comfortleſs, all alone, and at laſt was delivered of
                        two fair boys, in the deſolate foreſt. Theſe children were no ſooner come into the world, but a freſh miſery happened to this
                        lady; for as ſhe lay under the tree, her two infants by her, ſuddenly came a huge bear, moſt terrible to behold, and took up
                        one of the infants in his mouth, and with great pace haſted into the thickeſt of the foreſt. This ſtrange and unlooked for
                        accident, frighted the diſtreſſed lady to the ſoul, that ſhe cried out moſt lamentably, ſcrambing upon her hands and knees to
                        go after the bear, who was quickly got out of her figut. But, alas! it little availed her, for ſhe never came to the ſight of
                        her child, until by a miracle, it was at length diſclosed. So long wandered this lady up and down, from place to place,
                        weeping for her child, that being weary with travail, ſhe fell ſick and was almoſt <fw type="catch" place="bottom">at</fw><pb
                            n="17"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 17</fw>at the point of death. In this condition we leave her,
                        and porceed to the other child ſhe left under the tree.</p>
                    <p>It happened the ſame day that her brother king Pepin had taken his journey from Paris, towards conſtantinople, to viſit his
                        ſiſter Belliſant; and ſtriking through Orleans, he made ſuch haſte, that he entered into the foreſt where his banished ſiſter
                        was lately delivered of two children, but knew not what happened. Now as the king paſſed through this foreſt, he ſpied lying
                        under a tree, alone, the other ſon of Belliſant; and he ſaid to his attendants, <said>my lords, ſee, I have here found a fair
                            encounter,</said>
                        <said>even a child;</said> ſaid the lords, <said>it is even ſo.</said>
                        <said>Take it up,</said> ſaid the king, <said>it ſhall be brought up at my charge as long as it lives, and be uſed as my own;
                            and ifi t lives to man's eſtate, I'll endow it with lands and poſſeſſions.</said> And calling to one of his 'ſquires, he
                        gave him charge of it, ſaying, <said>take this infant to Orleans, ſee it baptiſed, provide a nurſe for it, and let it want
                            nothing.</said> (The king little ſuſpecting that this child was his nephew.) The 'ſquire took the child to Orleans, had it
                        baptiſed, and gave it his own name, Valentine, and ſought a nurſe, and gave it <fw type="sig" place="bottom">B2</fw><fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">great</fw><pb n="18"/><fw type="header" place="top">THE HISTORY OF</fw>great attendance,
                        according to the king's command. This done, the king proceeded on his journey towards Conſtantinople, to ſee his beauteous
                        ſiſter Belliſant; but ere he could paſs through the foreſt, he chanced to meet with Blandiman, accompanied with a woman that
                        he had brought in order to aſſiſt his lady in her greateſt extremity of child-birth.</p>
                    <p>Bladiman ſeeing the king, knew him, and ſuddenly alighted from his horſe, doing his duty to him. The king perceiving it was
                        Blandiman, aſked what news, and how his ſiſter Belliſant did? Blandiman anſwered, <said>moſt gracious ſovereign, I muſt tell
                            you ſtrange news of your loving ſiſter, and how ſhe fiares: wherefore ſo it is, that by force of treaſon of the arch
                            prieſt of Conſtantinople, ſhe is baniſhed out of the emperor's court and dominions; and, but for the mercy of the lords of
                            the emperor's court and others, ſhe had been burt to aſhes in the ſight of all the people</said></p>
                    <p>King Pepin having heard the lamentable relation of Blandiaman, he broke out in bitter words againſt her, ſaying, <said>I think
                            the emperor no upright judge in ſparing the life of my ſiſter; for I ſwear, that if I had her now in my poſſeſſion, by
                            death I would <fw type="catch" place="bottom">make</fw><pb n="19"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON.
                                19</fw>make her an example to all falſe ladies, whilſt the world enfureth.</said> Then he commanded all his lords and
                        others to ſtay their journey, and return back to Paris; <said>for he grievous offences of my ſiſter, ſtay my journey.</said>
                        And ſo in that diſtruſt and melancholy, king Pepin returned towards Orleans. When Blandiman perceived the king thus angry and
                        ſurpriſed, he durſt proceed no farther in his relation of lady Belliſant, but leaving the king, took his way towards the great
                        tree, where he lately left her in the pains of child-birth; being come thither, he ſought for her every where, but could hear
                        no tidings of her; neither knew he which way to take. Being in this extremity, he tied his horſe to a thorn-tree, and began to
                        make a cloſer ſearch than before, and at length founf her lying flat on the earth, in a manner ſpeechleſs. Blandiman being
                        glad he had founf her, took her up in his arms, and ſet her on her feet, ſaying, <said>alas! dear lady, how came you to ſtray
                            ſo far from the place where I left you?</said></p>
                    <p>The lady replied, <said>"Ah! Blandiman, my diſtreſſes daily increaſe; for thou wert no ſooner gone, but I being delivered of
                            two babes, a ravenous bear aſſailed me, <fw type="cathch" place="bottom">and</fw><pb n="20"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                                >20 THE HISTORY OF</fw>and bore away one of themm and I endeavoured, though in vain, to overtake the ſavage creature,
                            leaving the other infant under the tree."</said>
                        <said>Lady,</said> quoth he, <said>the other infant! Why, I came but lately from the tree, and I am well aſſured there lay no
                            infant there,</said> at which ſhe fell into a ſwoon, and cried out, <said>"come death, and finiſh what sorrows have
                            brought on me."</said></p>
                    <p>All this while Blandiman heard her piteous complaints; at laſt ſhe betaking herſelf to her feet, he accompanied her, with a
                        woman he had brought with him, to a neighbouring village, where they lodged and nouriſhed her, until ſhe had recovered
                        ſtrength. Then Blandiman told her, how he by chance met with her brother, king Pepin; <said>and as ſoon as he underſtood that
                            the emperor had exiled you, he lightly gave credit that you were in the fault, and lays all the blame on you.</said></p>
                    <p><said>"O!</said>quoth the lady, <said>now what I moſt feared is come to paſs— I will never return again to Paris, but take my
                            way into ſome remote land, where my body with my faults ſhall be ſmothered, for my brother's anger is ſo great, that he
                            would willingly deliver me to death, therefore, it is better to fly and ſave my life, than fall into the <fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">fury</fw><pb n="21"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 21</fw>fury of ſo angry a
                            brother."</said>——This ſhe ſpoke with tears. Said Blandiman, <said>lady, dry up your tears, and be aſſured of my
                            fidelity;</said> and ſo they paſſed forth to expoſe themſelves to future dangers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
                    <ab>Of the bear that bore away one of the children.</ab>
                    <p>THE bear (as you have heard) that carried away one of the children, all this while had offered it no violence, but bore it to
                        her cave: In this cave the bear had four young ones, among whom ſhe laid the child to be devoured; yet tall this while the
                        young bears did it no harm, but with their rough paws ſtroked it ſoſtly.— The old bear perceiving they did not devour it,
                        ſhewed a beariſh kind of favor towards it, inſomuch that ſhe kept it, and gave it ſuck among her young ones for the ſpace of
                        one year. This child, by reaſon of the nouriſhment it received, became rough all over like a beaſt, and as he grew in
                        ſtrength, began to range up and down <fw type="catch" place="bottom">the</fw><pb n="22"/><fw type="header" place="top">22 THE
                            HISTORY OF</fw>the woods; and when he met with other beaſts would ſmite them, and got ſuch a maſtery over them, that they
                        began to ſhun the place where he came.———And in the beaſt-like eſtate he paſſed theterm of fifteen years, growing up to ſuch a
                        ſtrength, that ſcarce any man or beaſt in the foreſt durſt ſtir abroad leſt he ſhould kill them, and afterwards eat their
                        fleſh. His name was called Orſon, because a bear had been his nurſe.</p>
                    <p>Here we leave the wild man in the foreſt, and look to what became of the lady Belliſant and her ſervant Blandiman, and we will
                        ſuddenly find them wandering through ſeveral lands and countries: the lady ſtill bewailing the loſs of her two children. But
                        in the midſt of her ſorrow, yet paſſed on her weary journey, until at length ſhe came to a port, off Portugal, on which ſtood
                        an invincible caſtle, kept by a giant, called Ferragus, ſo large that there was no horſe to be found that could bear the
                        living trunk of this huge giant. It happened at this caſtle, that every ſhip that paſſed by that port, was to pay tribute to
                        this giant, which he himſelf daily came on voard to receive. At length he came into the ſhip where the <fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">lady</fw><pb n="23"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALWNTINE AND ORSON. 23</fw>lady Belliſant was, and
                        caſting his eyes about, he eſpied her; then kindly taking her by the hand, he led her into the caſtle by this wife, for he was
                        married to a beautiful lady. Blandiman followed his lady alſo, fearing the giant; but he behaved himſelf ſo nobly, that he did
                        not offer her the leaſt violence, but preſented her to his wife, who gladly received her; the giant having charged his wife to
                        uſe her and Blandiman honorably.</p>
                    <p>During their abode in the caſtle, ſhe would often ſhed tears for the loſs of her two children, and the lady of the caſtle would
                        often comfort her in the beſt manner ſhe could. And within this caſtle ſhe tarried a long time: and here we muſt leave her,
                        and return back to tell you ſomething of the emperor of Conſtantinople, and the arch prieſt.</p>
                    <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw>
                    <pb n="24"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">24 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. V.</head>
                    <ab>How by the counſel of the arch prieſt, new cuſtoms and taxations were raiſed thro' the city of Conſtantinople, and how the
                        treaſon came to light. How the emperor ſent for king Pepin, to ſee the combat fought between the arch prieſt and the
                        merchant.</ab>
                    <p>THE emperor having ſhamefully expelled Belliſant, his wife, often repented him of the fact; and the arch prieſt being an oracle
                        in his ears, inſomuch that he heaped new honors continually upon that traitorous wretch, advencing him above the higheſt in
                        the empire; whatever he commanded was effected. At laſt, having got all power and authority in his own hands, he began to
                        raiſe the cuſtoms and taxes of the city of Conſtantinople, which ſtruck to the hearts of the inhabitants. Amongſt theſe his
                        umpoſitions, it happened that according to their yearly cuſtom, there was held a great mart in the city, which was about the
                        month of September. Hereunto reforted a great number of people, eſpecially merchants. The <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >mart</fw><pb n="25"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 25</fw>mart day being come, the emperor gace the
                        charge thereof to this arch prieſt, who accordingly provided himſelf, and armed two hundred men to guard his own perſon. Being
                        thus accompanied, he took his way into the city.</p>
                    <p>It ſo chanced, that among the reſt of thoſe that ſold wares, the merchant was there preſent, of whom you have heard before,
                        viz. he that came riding by the way where Blandiman, the lady's 'ſquire, and the traitorous arch prieſt were fighting. The
                        arch prieſt perceived him, but took no notice of him, for he was fearful that all his villainy ſhould come to light. The ſight
                        of the merchant much troubled the arch prieſt, ſo that he wiſhed his death, and would have effected the ſame by the authority
                        he now had, but that he feared ſome great tumult would ariſe thereby. Now mark what followed: "The merchant was furniſhed with
                        coſtly wares, as cloth of golf, ſilver, ſilk, &amp;c. and took more money than any five merchants beſide. The fair being
                        ended, the arch prieſt ſent forth his officer to demand his accuſtomed duties. One officer came to the merchand, and ſaid,
                            <said>"Sir, you muſt pay rod <!-- THIS WORD IS WEIRD -->on every pound you have <fw type="sig" place="bottom">C</fw><fw
                                type="catch" place="bottom">taken,</fw><pb n="26"/><fw type="header" place="top">26 THE HISTORY OF</fw>takenm it being
                            o ordered by the offieers <!-- this is weird too --> to whom it belongs."</said> He at this being angry, ſaid,
                            <said>curſed be the diſloyal arch prieſt, for he is the only cauſe of theſe new raiſed exactions; it had been well if he
                            had long ſince had his deſert, and with ſhame and infamy ended his days.</said> At which reporachful words, the officer
                        took his ſtaff and ſtruck the merchant on the head, ſo that presently the blood guſhed out: then the merchant drew his ſword,
                        and truck the officer, ſo that he laid him at his feet for dead.</p>
                    <p>Upon this aroſe a gret rout through the fair, inſomuch that the other officers, coming up to help their fellow, took the
                        merchant and carried him before the arch prieſt. The arch prieſt would have put him to death, but the merchany appealed to
                        juſtice to have his cauſe tried by law. The arch prieſt fearing the people, ſent him away to the emperor: for nothing could
                        ſatisfy him but his life; but in ſeeking the life of the merchant, he perchaſed his own death. The emperor in perſon ſat as
                        judge, and the arch prieſt brought his advocate to plead his cauſe, which was, <hi>"That the merchangt had committed murder,
                            and had ſpoken opprobious words againſt the <fw type="catch" place="bottom">arch</fw><pb n="27"/><fw type="header"
                                place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 27</fw>arch prieſt."</hi> The advocate having ended his accuſation, the merchant fell
                        on his knees before the emperor, and ſaid, <hi><said>"Moſt excellent prince, give me but audience, and I ſhall unfold a matter
                                of ſuch importance, that it touches yourperſon in the higheſt degree of treaſon."</said></hi>
                        <said>Say on,</said> ſaid the emperor, <hi><said>"mighty emperor, I adviſe you to make faſt the gates about your palace, that
                                none depart this place."</said></hi> The emperor did as he requeſted. <said>Then,</said> ſaid the merchant, <said>"all
                            you that love the honor of the emperor, attend my words; the time is come that the treaſon of the curſt atch prieſt will
                            be revealed, and come to light: great emperor, this is that curſed man that you have nouriſhed and brought to great honor,
                            who hath deceived his truſt; for he it is that hath wrought all the diſcord between you and your virtuous lady whom you
                            have baniſhed from your bed, and by whom you have received more diſhonor, than he ever recieved honor from you; for he
                            ſecretly , and underhandedly, made love to the empreſs: but ſhe denied him; and he perceiving there was no likelihood to
                            accompliſh his deſire, it drove him into fearthat his diſloyal act would come to light, and therefore deviſed to flaſify
                            unto your <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ears</fw><pb n="28"/><fw type="header" place="top">28 THE HISTORY OF</fw> ears
                            her unfaithful love to your bed. All which his falſe accuſations, I will here unfold the truth of what theſe eyes were
                            witneſſes.</said></p>
                    <p><said>It happened on a day, after the baniſhment of the empreſs, as I was riding about my affairs, I chanced to travel thro' a
                            wood, and found the treacherous prieſt transformed out of the habit of a prieſt into that of a knight, ready for combatl
                            Drawing nearer, I beheld him fighting with another man armed; who, at laſt, I found to be Blandiman, 'ſquire to the
                            baniſhed lady, who conducted her in the time of her exile. I perceiving they encountered each other ſo fiercely, I called
                            to them to give over, but thy little regarded me. I perceived the lady weeping, and at laſt ſhe ſaid unto me,
                                    <hi><said>"gentle merchant, aſſiſt me againſt this treacherous arch prieſt, that ſeeketh by force to rob me of my
                                    honor: This is he by whom I am baniſhed from my emperor's bed and country."——</said></hi> With that I put ſpurs to
                            my horſe, and ran between them to part them: which the arch prieſt preceiving, he fled into the wood. I well knowing who
                            he was, noble emperor, it had been my part to have revealed this long ago, but durſt not, for fear <fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">his</fw><pb n="29"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 29</fw>his greatness ſhould have
                            brought me to an untimely death.</said></p>
                    <p>The emperor hacing heard all this, he ſighed, and at laſt fell into tears:—then turned to the arch prieſt, ſaying,
                                <hi><said>"well I have ſeen now what I have ever miſtruſted! Thou haſt made me of all men moſt unhappy!—Thy treaſon
                                hath bewitched me, in an evil hour I gace credit to thy falſe tongue!"</said></hi></p>
                    <p>The emperor ſeeing the merchant ſo reſolute, he ſaid, <said>"arch prieſt, it is time that thou either acquit thyſelf by
                            anſwering this challenge, or yeild theyſelf guilty of what has been laid to thy charge."</said> The arch prieſt replied,
                            <said>"mighty emperor, to anſwer to the merchant's challenge is con<fw type="sig" place="bottom">C2</fw><fw type="catch"
                                place="bottom">trary</fw><pb n="30"/><fw type="header" place="top">30 THE HISTORY OF</fw>trary to my place and
                            calling, for I am a ſacred prelate of the church, and therefore I may refuſe to fight."</said>
                        <hi><said>"Nay,</said> ſaid the emperor, <said>in this caſe no excuſe is to be admitted; but you muſt either fight or yeild
                                yourſelf a traitor to my crown and dignity."</said></hi> At theſe words the arch prieſt was ſore troubled in mind,
                        yet, at laſt, he was fain to accept the combat. So the emperor commanded them both to ſafe keeping, until he had ſent letters
                        to king Pepin of France.</p>
                    <p>The ambaſſadors, after long travel, arrived at Tome, where they found king Pepin; the ambaſſadors then ſaid, <hi><said>"great
                                lord, we preſent theſe letters from Alexander your brother, emperor of Conſtantinople, of which we entreat a ſpeedy
                                anſwer."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>King Pepin took the letters graciouſly, and read them, after which he ſaid, <said>"my lords, the emperor ſends me word, that my
                            ſiſter Belliſan has been wrongfully baniſhed; and that, by reaſon of a falſe arch prieſt, to whom he gave too much truſt;
                            which prieſt, for theſe treaſonable facts, is accuſed by a merchant, who has challenged this treacherous prieſt to ſingle
                            combat. Now the day and place is ready for the trial of this fact, whereby I <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ſhall</fw><pb
                                n="31"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 31</fw>ſhall be fully ſatisfied, whether my ſiſter has been
                            guilty of what she has been charged with, and ſhamefully baniſhed for. Upon all which, I ſwear and vow by my crown and
                            dignity, that if the emperor has offered this indignity without cauſe, I will be revenged of him in the extremeſt manner
                            that war can thunder forth."</said> Having ended his ſpeech to his lords, in the preſence of the ambaſſadors, he commanded
                        that every man ſhould accompany him to Conſtantinople, to behold this fight between the merchant and the arch prieſt.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
                    <ab>How the merchant and the arch prieſt encountered about the clearing of the lady Belliſant; and what a glorious victory did
                        betide the merchant.</ab>
                    <p>NOW was the day appointed come for the combat between the arch prieſt and the merchant; and every thing was in readineſs,
                        according to the command of the emperor. At last came both com<fw type="catch" place="bottom">batants</fw><pb n="32"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">32 THE HISTORY OF</fw>batants into the fild, and preſented themſelves before the emperor. The
                        arch prieſt was armed in a most ſumptuous armour of preoof, all emboſſed with gold and pearl, that it dazzled the eyes of the
                        beholders. The arch prieſt came forth in the field, and took his place appointed him at one end of the lift. The emperor
                        beholding the glorious ſhow that the arch prieſt made in his arms, called forthe the merchant cauſing him firſted to kneel
                        down, and in the preſence of the aſſembly dybbed him knight: Then he commanded that a rich armour ſhould be put on him, in the
                        preſence of king Pepin, who during the time he was arming, promiſed this merchant if he overcame the arch prieſt, to advance
                        him to great livings and high authority.</p>
                    <p>Theſe two adverſaries being now in redineſs, their horſes were brought forth, and they mounted, ready to give battle. The
                        emperor gave ſtrict charge to all his officers of arms, to have a ſpecial eye upon the arch prieſt, leſt he ſhould fly the
                        field, or run away from them. The merchant being mounted, and his ſword girt on him, firſt entered the liſts; then came the
                        arch prieſt, accompanied with nobels of great honor and dignity. The combatants thus <fw type="catch" place="bottom"
                            >entered</fw><pb n="33"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 33</fw>entered the liſts, ready to charge each
                        other; king Pepin called out aloud to the merchant, ſaying, <said>My friend, may God give thee victory over this falſe
                            traitor:</said> The merchant replied, <said>Dread king, I doubt not but this might to make this traitorous prieſt confeſs,
                            that he has villanouſly ſought the deſtruction of your ſiſter.——</said> Then came a herald, and adminiſtered to them both
                        an oath; and after clearing the lifts, left the champions to their fortunes. The marſhals of the field brought each of them a
                        ſpear, which they had no ſooner recieved, but they put ſpurs to their horſes, and ran with ſuch violence together, that their
                        ſpears were broken in their hands: then they ſet forward for another courſe, charging each other with their ſwords, in ſuch a
                        violent manner, that they cut off hwole quarters of the croſſets: the arch prieſt ſeeing himſelf ſo ſtiffly matched, gave over
                        the fight until towards evening, for ſuch was the cuſtom of the country, thinking thereby to weary out the merchant; which the
                        merchant perceiving, he prepared to meet the arch prieſt courageouſly when he encountered him, which being not long after the
                        merchant ſo redoubled his ſtrokes, that he cut off one of his <fw type="catch" place="bottom">ears;</fw><pb n="34"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">34 THE HISTORY OF</fw>ears; and with the violence of the ſame blow, the merchant's ſword fell
                        from his hand; which the arch prieſt ſeeing, put ſpurs to his horſe, and charged him with ſuch violence, that he ran againſt
                        the merchant;s horſe, and thruſt out one of his eyes; the horſe feeling himself hurt, ran up and down as mad, leaping ſo
                        furiouſly that he threw his rider; the merchant's foor hung in the ſtirrup, whereby he was in great danger. King Pepin was ſo
                        diſcouraged at this diſaſter, that the tears trickled down his cheeks.</p>
                    <p>Now that which was more miraculous was, that all the time the merchant was dragged up and down the field, with his foot hanging
                        in the ſtirrup, the arch prieſt could not force his horſe forward, btu fled to and fro, ſo that he could not make a prey of
                        the merchant, as he intended. But at laſt the merchant's horſe fell down, and he got his foot clear of the ſtirrup.</p>
                    <p>The prieſt perceiving he had recovered his legs, ran with violence upon him, and gave him five or ſix ſuch blows upon his
                        ſhoulders, that the poor merchant was aſtonished. At laſt he was forced to give back, to recover breath; and in a little time
                        he gave a freſh aſſault upon the arch <fw type="catch" place="bottom">prieſt</fw><pb n="35"/><fw type="header" place="top"
                            >VALENTINE AND ORSON. 35</fw>prieſt with ſuch violence that the ſword fell out of his hand; but he at firſt ſo wounded
                        him, that the blood rant through his armour upon the earth. This ſo vexed the prieſt, that he grew mad with rage, and turned
                        his horſe upon the merchant, thinking to have over-run him; but the merchant obſering his drift, prepared to receive him, and
                        drawing a long knife, punched it into the belly of the horſe, which made him fling and leadp, ſo that the prieſt was like to
                        have been unhorſed, and ſtriving to ſabe himſelf, he loſt his ſhield. The merchant ſeeing him unarmed, ran haſtily and caught
                        up his ſhield, and caſt it awayl and then making towards his horſe, ſmote him hin the belly with his ſword, which brought both
                        horſe and rider to the ground.</p>
                    <p>The prieſt being thus unhorſed, endeavored to recover himſelf; but the merchant gave him sucj a blow, that he laid him flat to
                        the ground again, and leaping on him, pulled off his helmet, thinking to have ſmitten off his head. The atch prieſt ſeeing
                        himſelf in ſuch danger, ſaid, <said>I pray thee, friend, take pity on me, and give me leave to confeſs myſeld; for I yeild
                            myſelf vanquiſhed.</said> The merchant was <fw type="catch" place="bottom">very</fw><pb n="36"/><fw type="header"
                            place="top">36 THE HISTORY OF</fw>very corteous, and granted his requſt. The arch prieſt was no ſooner got on his feet,
                        but claſping the merchant in his arms, threw him on the ground, and leaping upon him, ſaying to the merchant, <said>I have now
                            an advantage over thee, and thou ſhalt not eſcape with life, if thou doſt not effect what I command thee.</said>
                        <said>Ah!</said> ſaid the merchant, <said>haſt thou betrayed me? well, I ſtand at thy mercy; therefore let me know what thou
                            commandeſt.</said>
                        <said>Then,</said> ſaid the prieſt, <said>go with me to the emperor and king Pepin, and teſtify that thou haſt falſely accuſed
                            me; which if thou wilt do, I promiſe thee to ſabe thy life.</said> The merchant having heard what the prieſt ſaid, was
                        very ſorrowful; but at length he thus answered, <said>ſir, prieſt, I am ready to accompliſh thy deſires, ſo let us go to the
                            emperor, and there I will ſet you free from all the accuſations which I have exhibited againſt you.</said>
                        <said>Very well,</said> ſaid the arch prieſt, <said>then let us go together.</said></p>
                    <p>The merchant had no ſooner got on his feet, but he began afreſh to pen the treason of the arch prieſt, even to his teethl and
                        again he took courage, and ſuddenly claſping the arch prieſt in his arms, threw him on the ground, and having him at <fw
                            type="catch" place="bottom">advantage</fw><pb n="37"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 37</fw>advantage,
                        he ſaid, <said>arch prieſt, ſeeing that you have taught me to play my pary, think no more on confeſſions, for you ſhall
                            confeſs to me, or none.</said> The arch prieſt ſeeing himſelf beat at his own weapons, began agian to entreat; but the
                        merchant not regarding him, preſently put out his eyes, and gave him ſo many deadly blows, that he ſecured him from doing him
                        any further harm. Then the merchant called the marſhals of the field, and ſaid, <hi><said>"Lo, here you may ſee I have done my
                                endeavour againſt the arch prieſt; and if he is vanquiſhed, ſay ſo: And my requeſt is, that you would conduct
                                Alexander, the emperor of Conſtantinople, and king Pepin of France, to this place, that they may be
                                ear-witneſſes<!-- not sure if this is correct hyphenation --> of the confeſſion which the arch prieſt ſhall make to
                                them."</said></hi></p>
                    <p>The marſhals did according to the requeſt of the merchant , and perſently the emperor and king Pepin went to the place where
                        the arch prieſt lay vanquiſhed.</p>
                    <p>When the emperor and the king, with the reſt of the nobles, had head the vilainout prieſt acknowledged that the empreſs was
                        entirely innocent, and that the wicked plot was all of his own forming, who can expreſs the joy and ſorrow of <fw type="sig"
                            place="bottom">D</fw><fw type="catch" place="bottom">theſe</fw><pb n="38"/><fw type="header" place="top">38 THE HISTORY
                            OF</fw>theſe two mighty potentates, and of the reſt of the aſſembly?</p>
                    <p>The firſt thing that was determined, was the execution of this wicked prieſt, which being finiſhed, the emperor came to king
                        Pepin, and in the moſt friend'y and passionate manner, endeavored to excuſe himſeld to him for the siſgrace of his ſiſter;
                        vowing, as a true mark of the ſenſe of his indeiſcretion, he would be his ſervant to the end of his life; upon whic ha
                        perpetual peace was made between them; and king Pepin, but not without ſome heavy cognitations, ſet forward for his own
                        country.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
                    <ab>How Haufrey and Henry repined at the king's love to Valentine.</ab>
                    <p>IT happened one day, when the king was at dinner, and Valentine was attending upon him, that the king called to him, and in
                        hearing of all his nobles, told him, that he was indebted to him for the preſervation of his life, and for many other ſignal
                        acts of duty and ſervice; and that in conſideration thereof, he freely gave him the earldom of Clair<fw type="catch"
                            place="bottom">mond,</fw><pb n="39"/><fw type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 39</fw>mond, and would be ſure to
                        ſhew him further marks of his favor, the firſt opportunity.</p>
                    <p>This new decalration fo the king's, gave the two brothers, Haufrey and Henry, freſh cauſe for malice and jealouſy, inſomuch
                        that they contrived daily plots to take away his life; which Valentine not ſuſpecting, went on cheerfully in the king's
                        ſervice, and grew every day more and more in his favor. But leave we at this preſent, to return a little to his brother Orſon,
                        againſt whom ſuch frequent complaints were brought to court, that the king, with the advice of his nobles, iſſued out his
                        proclaimation, whth a reward of two thouſand crowns for any that ſhould take this furious wild man, either alive or dead, and
                        bring his head before him.</p>
                    <p>Hereupon aſſembled many knights to take this affair in hand; and whilſt the king was debating with them, Haufrey , Valentine's
                        enemy, being there, propoſed to the king to ſend Valentine, <said>who having offered unlawful love to your daughter Eglantin,
                            he is the fitteſt to fight this ſavage, whom, if he vanquiſhes, let him have her in marriage.</said>
                        <fw type="catch" place="bottom">CHAP.</fw></p>
                    <pb n="40"/>
                    <fw type="header" place="top">40 THE HISTORY OF</fw>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
                    <ab>How Valentine conquers Orſon, his brother, a wild man in the woods of Orleans, and preſents him to king Pepin.</ab>
                    <p>NOW Valentine whent on his journey, and ſoon arrived in the foreſt; but it being night, he tied his horſe to a tree and betook
                        himſelf to the top for his ſecurity. As ſoon as it was day, looking round him, he ſaw his brother Orſon coming towards him,
                        and coming to the tree where the horſe was tied, and having never ſeen ſuch a horſe before, he began to ſcratch and tear him
                        with his nails; upon which the horſe grew mad, and kicked at him with great fury.</p>
                    <p>Valentine perceiving his horſe in danger, cried out aloud, and ſaid, <said>"wild man, leave my horſe."</said> The wild man,
                        hearing a ſtrange voice, looked up to the tree, and ſeeing a man, made divers ſigns for him to come down. Valentine making all
                        the haſte he could, drew his ſword, which when Orſon ſaw, he leaped back, but ſuddenly returned again upon Valentine, and
                        threw him on the ground. Being thus grovelling on the ground, Valen<fw type="catch" place="bottom">tine</fw><pb n="41"/><fw
                            type="header" place="top">VALENTINE AND ORSON. 41</fw>tine eſſayed divers times to have gotten Orſon under him. When he
                        ſaw that by strength there was no hope to overcome him, he pulled out a ſharp pointed knige, and ſmote Orſon in the ſide; he
                        ſeeing himſelf wounded, fiercely aſſulted Valenine with his ſharp nails: They fought ſo long together, that it is too tedious
                        here to relate; however, ſo long, that they both gre faint. In which tediouſneſs, bothe ſtanding gaping upon each other,
                        Valentine looked ſtedfaſtly upon him, made ſigns to him he would give him food and raiment befitting a human creature. Orſon
                        understood his meaning, and made ſigns also, that he would obey him in every thing he deſired. And thus Valentine conquered
                        the wild man.</p>
                    <p>All this adventure being ended in this manner,</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
