<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!-- The two cover pages should go here -->
         <pb n="4"/>
         <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">The <lb/>History <lb/>of <lb/>Valentine <!-- should I endode the size and difference of type? -->
            <lb/>and <lb/>Orson.</head>
         <figure>
            <figDesc>Line <!-- Maybe this is how I should do this? maybe i should take this out? --></figDesc>
         </figure>
         <p><persName>Pepin</persName>, King of France, had a sister named <persName>Bellisant</persName>, whose hand was demanded by several kings
            and princes. Her choice fell on <persName>Alexander</persName>, Emperor of <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, who came to the court of
               <persName>King Pepin</persName> to espouse her, and then escourt her home in state as his bride.</p>
         <p><persName>Alexander's</persName> Prime minister
            <!-- should this be encoded in total as a persName because this is a new character or just alex because he has already been done?  -->,
            and a favorite, was a shelfish and cruel arch-priest, who, fearing the lovely empress would soon usurp his influence wover the emperor,
            resolved to effect her destruction.</p>
         <p>The emperor, being of a suspicious disposition, the arch priest worked upon it for some time, at first; and then one day, when the emperor
            was alone, he entered his apartments, and said;— " Mighty king, may heaven guard your majesty from the treacherous designs of your
            empress: who, not content with faithfulness to your sacred person, now seeks to destroy even your life,"</p>
         <pb n="5"/>
         <!-- need the image facs -->
         <fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and Orson.</fw>
         <p>The emperor, implicitly believing the priest, could not restrain his fury ; but rushing into his wife's apartment, he in a savage manner,
            dragged her about by the hair, exclaiming,<said>"Base Wretch! I am but too well informed of your infamous proceedings!"</said> Then
            dashing her on the ground, her left her, desiring her to prepare herslef for death.</p>
         <p>The empress having by the help of her attendants, somewhat recovered, sought the emperor, and falling on her knees thus addressed
               him,—<said>"Oh take pity on one who has ever faithfully loved you! I shall soon become a mother; and I implore your compassion on
               behalf of my child! let me be imprisoned until its birth ; and then, if your anger be not appeased, do with me as you please ; but, oh!
               save my child!</said><!-- there is no ending quotation mark, but I am assuming this is where her speaking ends -->The emperor replied,
               <said>"Perish, base woman,and the child of your perfidy with you!"</said> when the courtiers, seeing any further appeal would but
            increase his rage removed <persName>Bellisant</persName> from his presence.</p>
         <p>Her faithful servant, <persName>Blandiman</persName>, now threw himseld at her feet, imploring her to leave her barbsrous husband, and
            suffer him to conduct her to her brother's court, but she refused, as that would imply a confession of guilt.</p>
         <p>The emperor banidhed his queen, instead of putting her to death, but forbade all persons, except her faithful attendant,
               <persName>Blandiman</persName>, to assist her, on pain of death. Thus accompanied, she soon reached the forest of Orleans, when
            overcome with fatigur, she sank on a couch made up of withered leaves and moss, prepared by her devoted servant, who then hastened away,
            to procure <pb n="6"/><fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">alentine and Orson.</fw> some assistance. Suring
               <persName>Blandiman</persName>'s absence the poor lady gave birth to two beautiful boys, when just as she was pressing them to her
            bosom as huge bear rushed upon her, and snatching up<figure/> one of the babes in its mouth, darted off inot the thickest of the forest
            with it. The wretched mother pursued, uttering the wildest shrieks, until exhausted by terror, she fell into a swoon, at the mouth of the
            monster's cave</p>
         <pb n="6"/>
         <fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and Orson.</fw>
         <!-- Why are there two page 6es? -->
         <p>It chanced that <persName>King Pepin</persName> was that day hunting in the forest, and passing near the spot where the other infant laid,
            was surprised to see the little beauty, who held out his tiny arms, as if to ask for protection. <said>"See, my lords,"</said> said
               <persName>King Pepin</persName>, <said>"this lovely infant appears to solicit my favour; I will adopt it as my own."</said> He then
            delivered the babe to one of the pages, who took it to a nurse, and by the royal command, it recieved the name of Valentine.</p>
         <p>Scarcely had the page galloped off when the king met <persName>Blandiman</persName>, and demanded what news from
               <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, when hearing that the arch-priest has accused his royal sister of plotting the emperor's death,
            he declared his belief in its truth, and blamed the emperor for sparing her life, adding, <said>"Let her beware how she comes inot my
               power."</said></p>
         <p><persName>Blandiman</persName> now sought his mistress, whom he found half distracted with her accumulated miseries, She related to him
            the birth and dreadful loss of her infant, and learning her brother's unjust wrath against her, resolved to take shelter in a
            monastery.</p>
         <p>The bear that carried away the infant, took it to her cave, and laid it before her younf; the cubs, however, instead of devouring it,
            fondled it which the old one percieving, gave it suck and the child grew string and hearty. As he increased in size and strength, he
            ranged the forest attacking the wild beast with such fury, that they dare not approach the cave in which he continued <pb n="7"/><fw
               type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and Orson.</fw> to reside with the old bear till his eighteenth
            year, when his strength was so amazing, and the terror he caused in all the country rouch, so great, that his renown spread all over
               <placeName>France</placeName>. He was called <persName>Orson</persName>, from having been nurtured by a bear.</p>
         <p><persName>Valentine</persName>, meanwhile, had been brought up with the king's daughter, <persName>Eglantine</persName>, to whom he was
            passionately attached. He was highly accomplished and brave, having greatly distinguished himself against the <name>Saracens</name> whom
            he conquered; and the favours showered on him excited the hatred of the king's sons, <persName>Henry</persName> and
               <!-- This is a little hard to see because of the string.. --><persName>Haufrey</persName>, they plotted to destroy him. A petition from
            the peasants, praying protection against <persName>Orson</persName>, dead or alive, on which <persName>Henry</persName> told his royal
            sire, that he thought no one so qualified to undertake this hazardous enterprise as the foundling <persName>Valentine</persName>, adding,
               <said>"and perhaps, if he conquers the savage, you eill reward him with the hand of out sister, <persName>Eglantine</persName>."</said>
            The kings, seeing their envy, frowned displeasure; but <persName>Valentine</persName>, hinting that the advice was given in the hope of
            encompassing his death, declared that it concerned his honor, and would brave the danger willingly, to preserve it unsullied.</p>
         <p>At the first dawn of morning, <persName>Valentine</persName> arose and putting on his armour, took a shield, polished like a mirror, and
            having arrived at the forest, he climbed a high tree near the <pb n="8"/><fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)"
               >Valentine and Orson.</fw> bear's cave. Presently he heard <persName>Orson</persName>, who had a buck with him which he had just killed
            coming roaring by; and he could not help admiring the beauty of his make, and his agility, wiching it were possible to tame him. He then
            tore off the branch of a tree, and threw it at <persName>Orson</persName>, who, looking up, uttered a furious howl and darted up the tree
            like lightning. <persName>Valentine</persName> descended, and <persName>Orson</persName>, seeing him on the ground, rushed down, when
               <persName>Valentine</persName>, holding up his shield, <persName>Orson</persName>, evidently surprised and delighted, beheld his own
            image. <persName>Valentine</persName> then lowered the shield, when <persName>Orson</persName>, tearing up a huge tree by the roots,
            attacked him, and a dreadful fight ensued. <persName>Orson</persName> recieving many wounds. The bear, hearing
               <persName>Orson's</persName> cries, now rushed forth, when <persName>Valentine</persName> aimed a blow, which would have hilled her,
            had not <persName>Orson</persName> rushed forward and throwing one arm round its neck, with supplicating gestures seemed to beg that he
            would not hurt her. <persName>Valentine</persName>, in token of kindness, then offered <persName>Orson</persName> some grapes and a bottle
            of strong liquor, which he no sooner tasted, then he gave them to the bear, throwing his arms round her whilst she devoured them, and she
            uttering a gentel growl, to express her satisfaction. The strong liquor, however, soon caused her death; on which
               <persName>Orson</persName> stood for a few moments motionless, supposing her to be only asleep; then he endeavoured to rouse her, but
            finding all his efforts ineffectual, his grief was scarcely to be described, uttering the most piercing shrieks and moand. At length,
               ap-<pb/><fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and Orson.</fw>proaching
               <persName>Valentine</persName>, he made signs that he would now become his; and tears running down his cheeks meanwhile, he suffered
            him to bind his hands, then followed him.</p>
         <p><persName>Valentine</persName> took his way towards the palace, followed by crowds, anxious to see this celebrated wonder; but when he
            came to the gate of the palace, the porter, affrighted, barred it and fled <!-- There should probably be a period here -->
            <persName>Valentine</persName>made a sign to <persName>Orson</persName>, who tearing up a huge stone post, battered the gate to pieces
            which so alarmed the king and princess, that they would have fled for safety had not <persName>Valentine</persName> called to them, and
            assured them that <persName>Orson</persName> was no longer a savage; on which the king permitted him to be brought, and the whole court
            were delighted at him, especially when, on Valentine's making sighns, he kissed the hand of the fair <persName>Princess
               Eglantine</persName>.</p>
         <p>Soon after, a herald from the <persName>Dike of Acquitan</persName> sommonsed all true knights to avenge the cause of the <persName>Lady
               Fezon</persName>, whom the <persName>Green Knight</persName> held in captivity, proclaiming, that whoever conquered him should recieve
            her hand in marriage.</p>
         <p>The knight was so famous, that all except <persName>Valentine</persName> refused to engage with him, and the princess<note>The princess
               Eglantine</note> resolved, if possible, to save him by combatting the <persName>Green Knight</persName> herself, contrived to steal his
            armour, whilst he slept, and galloped off. <persName>Valentine</persName> heading this when he awoke, set out, attended by
               <persName>Orson</persName>, and arrived just as she was almost overpowered, when he rushed with fury on the <persName>Green
               Knight</persName>, who, demanding a <pb n="9"/><fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and
               Orson.</fw> parley, said, <said>"Brave Knight, in pity to they youth, I tell thee, unless thous canst remoce yonder shield thou ne'er
               canst conquer me."</said>
            <persName>Valentine</persName> flew to it, but could not stir it, when the <figure/><persName>Green Knight</persName> exclaimed,
               <said>"Know that none living can subdue me, except he was suckled by a wild beast,"</said>
            <persName>Valentine</persName> ran to <persName>Orson</persName>, who seixing the enchanted shield, instantly loosened <pb n="11"/><fw
               type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and Orson.</fw> it, and it fell to the ground. The
               <persName>Green Knight</persName> sprang upon <persName>Orson</persName>, but he dashed him to the ground, and would have destroyed
            him, but for <persName>Valentine.</persName> Thus subdued, he said, <said>This is a mystery; haste to my brother's castle, where the
                  <name>Braxen Head</name> will explain to you who my conqueroe is."</said> They proceeded thither at once, dinging the castle guarded
            by two lions, who, at <persName>Orson's</persName> approach, crouched down, when a dwarf came foth and conducted them to the <name>Brazen
               Head</name>, which then spoke as follows;—</p>
         <p><said>"Thou <persName>Valentine the brave, art son to the <persName>Emperor Alexander,</persName> by <persName>Bellisant</persName>, his
                  queen, who was unjustly banished; and the wild man, <persName>Orson</persName>, is thy brother. You were both born in the forest of
                     <placeName>Orleans</placeName>; you was found, and brought up by your uncle, <persName>King Pepin</persName>, but
                     <persName>Orson</persName> was stolen, and nurtured by a bear. Proceed home, where you will find your hapless mother, and as soon
                  as she embraces your brother, his speech wil be given to him."</persName></said></p>
         <p>The <name>Beazen Head</name> then fell; the castle tottered; darkness enshrouded them; and when the light was restored, no traces of the
            castle were to be seen. Then, having embraced each other, they proceeded to the court of <placeName>France</placeName>.</p>
         <p>The wicked arch priest, on his death bed, confessed he had basely slandered the empress, when the emperor set off for
               <placeName>France</placeName>, and releasing her from the monsatery, they repaired to the palace of her brother, who, together with her
            husband implored her forgiceness</p>
         <p>The nobel youths now presented themselves <pb n="12"/><fw type="header" place="top" rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Valentine and
               Orson.</fw> and no sooner had the empress thrown her arms round <persName>Orson</persName> than speech was given to him; when the
               <persName>Duke of Acquitain</persName>, taking his hand presented him to <persName>Lady Fezon</persName> as her future husband, and
               <persName>King Pepin</persName>, at the same time, joined the hands of <persName>Valentine</persName> and the <persName>Princess
               Eglantine</persName>.</p>
         <p>Splendid preperations were immediately set on foot for the celebration of their nuptials, and nothing was to be heard throughout the
            empire for a considerable time, but feasts and balls, and fireworks and illuminations, with every other kind of gorgeous and magnificent
            entertainment and rejoicing.</p>
         <ab rend="case(allcaps) align(center">Finis.</ab>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
