<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The History and Adventures of the Renowned Princes Valentine &amp; Orson</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Printed at Minerva Press in London for A.K. Newman and Co.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>From the internet archive.<!-- probably need more info here --></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>THE History and Adventures OF THE RENOWNED PRINCES VALENTINE &amp; ORSON</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <!-- I have no idea how to do this. I am going to fix it later... there are like two more pages of this that are weird and hard to transcribe so I am going to do them later. -->

         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The Empre<!-- I cant tell if this is a long s or not -->s Bellisant, driven from the Palace.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>Pepin of France, his sister gave, <lb/>To Greece's Emperor, great &amp; brave; <lb/>Whose breast by jealousy inflam'd, <lb/>His guiltleſs
            Queen, disgrac'd &amp; sham'd <lb/>He from his Palace turn'd astray, <lb/>To see to France, her lonely way.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The Bear taking one of her Children.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>At length she reach'd Orleans Wood, <lb/>Where faint with grief, &amp; want of food; <lb/>With sudden pains she was oppreſs'd, <lb/>And
            two fair Sons, her sight soon bleſs'd; <lb/>Then from the wood, came forth a Bear, <lb/>Who from her breast, one Child did tear.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The King finding the other Child.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>It happen'd that the King of France, <lb/>Was hunting in this wood, by chance; <lb/>When in amaze, he there did see, <lb/>A lovely babe,
            lie near a tree; <lb/>This child he said, <said>"I'll take as mine, <lb/>And call the Infant, Valentine."</said></ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>Orson destroying the Travellers.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>Now grown a man. In Pepin's Court, <lb/>There much prevail's a strange report; <lb/>That a wild man in Orleans Wood, <lb/>Each hapleſs
            Traveller made his food; <lb/>That limb from limb her them did tear, <lb/>And had been nourished by a Bear.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>Valentine <!-- can't read this --> the King's leave to fight Orson.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>The King himself, wish'd much to see, <lb/>This human beast, this Prodigy; <lb/>And Valentine the Foundling Knight, <lb/>Resolv'd this
            dreadful man to fight; <lb/>The King soon gave his kind consent, <lb/>And forth with joy, the Hero went.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>Valentine and Orson engag'd</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>The wild man found, from break of day, <lb/>Till night they fought without delay; <lb/>When Valentine by Art prevail'd <lb/>Where all his
            utmost strength had faild; <lb/>But little was he then aware. <lb/>'Twas his own brother, or a King's Heir.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>Valentine bringing Orson to the Palace.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>This tied he Orson home did bring, <lb/>To introduce him to the King: <lb/>Amaz'd the porter clos'd the gates. <lb/>Whilst Valentine
            impatient waits: <lb/>Orson at Court, grows civiliz'd, <lb/>And in due time, he is baptiz'd.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The King's Sons endeavoring to kill Valentine.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>The King's two Sons, in anger then, <lb/>Who were ambitions, envious men; <lb/>Resolv'd they Valentine would kill, <lb/>For gaining thus,
            the King's good will; <lb/> But Orson freed him from their rage, <lb/>For who could with his strength engage.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>Green Knight.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>Duke Savery was much distreſs'd, <lb/>For a Green Knight had him oppreſs'd; <lb/>Who swore he would his daughter take, <lb/>And this good
            Duke his captive make; <lb/>Unleſs he formd some Hero true, <lb/>Who could this Pagan Knight subdue.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption><!-- cant read this --></caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>To aid the Duke against his foe, <lb/>Brave Valentine &amp; Orson go; <lb/>And here fiar Frezon you behold, <lb/>Who gave to each a ring
            of Gold; <lb/>And vow'd that she his wife would be, <lb/>Who from the Green Knight set her free.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The Green Knight making friends of Valentine &amp; Orson</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>Now the Green Knight full well did know, <lb/>Orson would work his overthrow; <lb/>And therefore thonght it best to be, <lb/>On terms of
            peace and amity; <lb/>A Christian true, he then became, <lb/>And liv'd a Prince of Noble fame.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
         <figure>
            <caption>The Brazen Head declaring thier birth.</caption>
         </figure>
         <ab>The Brazen Head at length reveals, <lb/>The myst'ry which thier birth conceals; <lb/>The twins, thier virtnous Mother find, <lb/>And joy
            poſseſsed every mind; <lb/>The Princes each, take beauteous wives, <lb/>And many years live happy lives.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <pb/>
      </body>
      <back>
         <!-- There is an ad on the back cover. -->
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
