<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <head rend="align(center)">THE <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="slant(italic)">Valentine and Orson</hi></head>
         <lb/>
         <!-- pretty line here -->
         <ab rend="slant(italic) align(center)">Reader, you'll find this little Book contains <lb/>Engough to answer thy expense and pains; <lb/>And
            if with caution you will read it through, <lb/>'Twill both instruct, and delight thee too.</ab>
         <lb/>
         <!-- another pretty line -->
         <figure/>
         <!-- this one looks like a double helix -->
         <ab rend="align(center)">Printed for the Company of Walking Stationers.</ab>
         <pb/>
         <!-- Pretty star box -->
         <head rend="align(center)">THE <lb/>HISTORY <lb/>OF <lb/><hi rend="slant(italic)">Valentine and Orson</hi></head>
         <!-- Double helix line thing -->
         <ab rend="aligh(center) case(allcaps)">Chap. I.</ab>
         <ab rend="slant(italic)"><!-- Hanging indent -->The baniſhment of the <persName>Lady Belliſant</persName>, who is delivered of
               <persName>Valentine</persName> and <persName>Orſon</persName> at one Birth, in a wood,</ab>
         <p>I<!-- This is a super fancy I  -->T is recorded, that <persName>PEPEN</persName>, King of <placeName>France</placeName>, had a fair ſiſter
            named <persName>Belliſant</persName>, who was married to <persName>Alexander</persName>, the Emperor of <placeName>Greece</placeName>, and
            by him carried to his Capital at <placeName>Conſtantinople</placeName>; from whence, after having lived with great virtue, ſhe was
            baniſshed through the means of a falſe accuſer, whom the had ferverely check for his imprudence; and though at the ſame time ſhe was big
            with Child, yet ſhe was compelled to <pb n="3"/><fw rend="align(center)">( 3 )</fw> leave her huſband's empire, to the great regret of the
            people, attended only with a ſquire named <persName>Blandiman</persName>.</p>
         <p>After a great fatigue and travel, ſhe arrived in the foreſt of <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, where finding her pains come thick upon
            her, ſhe diſmiſſed her attendant for a midwife, but before his return was delivered of two lovely children, one of which was converyed
            away by a ſhe bear, but ſhe willing to ſave it purſused on her hands and knees, leaving the other behind.</p>
         <p>But before her return, <persName>King Pepin</persName> being hunting in the foreſt, came to the tree where ſhe left the other babe, and
            cauſing it to be taken up, ſent it to a nurſe, and when it grew up called his name
               <persName>Valentine</persName>.—<persName>Blandiman</persName> at length came back, and inſtead of finding his miſtreſs founf her
            brother <persName>Pepin</persName> at the tree, to which he declared all that had happened, and how his ſiſter was baniſhed through the
            falſe ſuggeſtions of the arch prieſst; which when <persName>King Pepin</persName> heard he was greatly enraged againſt the lady
               <persName>Belliſant</persName>, ſaying the Emperor ought to have put her to death; ſo leaving <persName>Blandiman</persName>, he
            returned to his nobles at <placeName>Paris</placeName>.—The lady <persName>Belliſant</persName> having followed the bear to no pur- <pb
               n="4"/><fw rend="align(center)">( 4 )</fw>poſe, returned to the place where ſhe had left the other babe; but great was her ſorrow when
               <persName>Blandiman</persName> ſaid he had ſeen her brother <persName>Pepin</persName>, but could tell nothing of the child; and having
            comforted her of the loſ of it, they went to the ſea-ſide took ſhipping, and arrived at the caſtle of the <persName>Giant
               Feragus</persName>, in <placeName>Portugal</placeName>.</p>
         <p>All this while the bear nouriſhed the infant amongſt her young ones, until at length it gre up a wild hairy man, doing great miſchief to
            all that paſſed thro' the foreſt; in which we will leave him, and return to the arch prieſt, who fif great miſchief, till he was imprached
            by a merchant of having wrongfully accuſed the Empreſs; upon which they fought, and the merchant conquering, made the prieſt confeſs all
            his treaſons, the Emperor wrote about it to the <persName>King of France</persName> and he was hanged.</p>
         <figure><!-- Lion and unicorn --></figure>
         <pb n="5"/>
         <fw rend="align(center)">( 5 )</fw>
         <!-- Pretty line -->
         <ab rend="case(allcaps) align(center)">Chap II.</ab>
         <ab rend="slant(italic) align(center)"><persName>Valentine</persName> conquers his Brother in the foreſt of
            <placeName>Orelans.</placeName></ab>
         <p>N<!-- Another fancy letter -->OW was <persName>Valentine</persName> grown a luſty young man, and by the <persName>King</persName> as
            greatly belived as if he had been his own ſon : commanding him to be taught the uſe of arms, in which he ſoon became ſo expert, that few
            in the court dared to encounter him : which made <persName>Hufray</persName> and <persName>Heny</persName> the King's baſtard ſons
            exceedingly envy him. At this junct<!-- There is not ct ligature... -->ure great complaints were made againſt the <persName>Wild
               Man</persName>, from whom no Knight had eſcaped with his life, and had encountered him: which made the King promiſe a thouſand marks to
            any that would bring him dead or alive, which offer none dare except; but <persName>Hufray</persName> and <persName>Henry</persName>
            defired <persName>King Pepin</persName> to ſend <persName>Valentine</persName>, with a view of getting rid of ſo powerful a rival in the
            the King's favour, but his Majeſty fleeing their malady, was very angry, telling them, he would rather loſe the beſt Baron in the
            land.</p>
         <pb n="6"/>
         <fw rend="align(center)">( 6 )</fw>
         <p>However <persName>Valentine</persName> defired leave of his Majeſty to go to the foreſt, reſolving either to conquer the <persName>Wild
               Man</persName>, or die in the attempt. Accordingly having furniſhed himſelf with a good horſe and arms, he ſet forward on his journey,
            and after two dayd travelling, he arrived in the foreſt; in the evening he tied his horſe to a large ſpreading oak, and got up in a tree
            himſelf, for his ſecurity, where he reſted that night.</p>
         <p>Next morning he beheld the <persName>Wild Man</persName> traverſing the foreſt in ſearch of his prey, at length he came to the tree where
            Valentine's horſe ſtood, from whom he pulled many hairs, upon which the horſe kicked him. The <persName>Wild Man</persName> feeling the
            pain, was going to tear him to pieces, which <persName>Valentine</persName> ſeeing, made ſigns as if he would fight him, and accordingly
            he leaped down, and gave him a blow, but the <persName>Wild Man</persName> caught him and threw him to the ground. Then taking up
            Valentine's ſhield, he behild it with amaze, with reſpect<!-- ct ligature --> to the divers colours thereon emblazoned.</p>
         <p><persName>Valentine</persName> being much bruiſed, got up and went towards his brother in great hanger: but <persName>Orſon</persName> ran
            to a tree, and the <pb n="7"/><fw rend="align(center)">( 7 )</fw> they engaged; but both being terrible wounded gave out by conſent; after
            which <persName>Valentine</persName> ſigned to <persName>Orſon</persName>, that if he would yield to him, he would order matters ſo as he
            ſhould become a rational creature.</p>
         <p><persName>Orſon</persName> thinking that he meant him no harm, ſtretched forth his hand to him; upon which he bound him, and then led him
            to Paris, where he preſented him to <persName>King Pepin</persName>, who had the <persName>Wild Man</persName> baptized by the name of
               <persName>Orſon</persName>, from his being taken in a wood. <persName>Orſon</persName>'s actions<!-- ct ligature --> during their ſtay
            there very much amuſed the court, and at length the <persName>Duck of <placeName>Acquitain</placeName></persName> ſent letters importin,
            that whoſoever would overthrow the <persName>Green Knight</persName>, a pagan champion, ſhould have his daughter
               <persName>Fazon</persName> in marriage. Upon which propſition <persName>Valentine</persName> ſet out for that province, attended by his
            brother <persName>Orſon</persName>, by which means he came to the knowledge of his parents, as we ſhall find hereafter.</p>
         <figure><!-- Lyre and horn --></figure>
         <pb n="8"/>
         <fw rend="align(center)">( 8 )</fw>
         <!-- pretty line -->
         <ab rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Chap. III</ab>
         <ab rend="slant(italic) align(center)">The fight between <persName>Orſon</persName> and the <persName>Green Knight</persName>.</ab>
         <p>A<!-- fancy giant letter -->FTER a long journey, <persName>Valentine</persName> and <persName>Orſon</persName> arrived at <persName>Duke
               Savary's</persName> palace in <placeName>Acquitain</placeName>; and making known the reaſon that they came there, were preſented to
               <persName>Fazon</persName>; to whom <persName>Valentine</persName> thus addreſſed himſeld:</p>
         <p><said>"Sweet creature, <persName>King Pepin</persName> has ſent me hither with the braveſt Knight in all his realm to fight the
                  <persName>Green Knight</persName>, who though he his numb and naked, is endued with ſuch valour, that no Knight under the ſun is
               able to cope with him."</said></p>
         <p>During this ſpeeched ſhe viewed <persName>Orſon</persName> narrowly, and he her; but ſupper coming in, interrupted them, and they ſat down
            to eat.</p>
         <p>Wilſt they were in the midſt of all ther feaſtings, the <persName>Green Knight</persName> entered ſaying, <said><persName>Duke
                  Acquitain</persName> haſt thou any more Knights to cope with me for thy daughter?</said>
            <said>Yes</said>, replied the Duke, <said>I have ſeventeen</said>, and then ſdhewed them to <pb n="9"/><fw rend="align(center)">( 9 )</fw>
            him. The <persName>Green Knight</persName> then ſaid to them, <said>est your fill, for to-morrow will be your laſt.
               </said><persName>Orſon</persName> hearing what he ſaid, was much incenſed againſt him, and ſuddenly riſing from the table, threw the
               <persName>Green Knight</persName> with ſuch force againſt the wall as laid him dead for ſome tiem; which very much pleased the whole
            company.</p>
         <p>Next day many Knights went to went to fight the <persName>Green Knight</persName>, but he overcame and ſlew them all; till at laſt,
               <persName>Orſon</persName> being armed in Vlaentine's armour, cam to the Green Knight's pavilion, and defying him, they began the moſt
            deſprate combat as ever was heard of, and the <persName>Green Knight</persName> made ſo great a ſtroke at him, as to cut the top of his
            helmit, and half his ſhield, and wounded him much. But this ſerved only to enrage the valiant <persName>Orſon</persName>, who coming up o
            him on foot, took hold of him, and pulled him from his horſe, got aſtride him, and was juſt going to kill him, but was prevented by the
            ſudden arrival of <persName>Valenine</persName>, who interceded with <persName>Orſon</persName> to ſpare his life, on the condition of his
            turning Chriſtian, and acuainting <persName>King Pepin</persName> how he was conquered.</p>
         <pb n="10"/>
         <fw rend="align(center)">( 10 )</fw>
         <p>The <persName>Green Knight</persName> having promiſed to perform all tat was deſired, they led him priſoner to the city of
               <placeName>Acquitain</placeName>, and the <persName>Duke</persName> recieved them with great joy, and offered the lady
               <persName>Fazon</persName> to <persName>Orſon</persName>; but he would not marry her till his brother had won the Green Knight's
            ſiſter, lday <persName>Clerimond</persName>; not till they had tolked with the enchanted head of braſs to know his parents, and get the
            proper uſe of his tongue; which when the lady knew ſhe was very ſorry, because ſhe loved <persName>Orſon</persName>, and was reſolved to
            marry none but him, who had so nobly conquered the <persName>Green Knight.</persName></p>
         <!-- There is a line of pretty stars here -->
         <ab rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Chap. IV.</ab>
         <ab rend="align(center) slant(italic)"><persName>Valentine</persName> and <persName>Orſon</persName> go in ſearch of <persName>Lady
               Clerimond</persName>, who had the <name>Brazen Head</name> in her poſſeſſion.</ab>
         <p><persName>V<!-- Fancu letter -->ALENTINE</persName> and <persName>Orſon</persName> having taken leave of the <persName>Duke of
                  <placeName>Acquitain</placeName></persName> and his dauther <persName>Fazon</persName>, proceeded on their journey in ſearch of the
            lady <persName>Clerimond</persName>, and at laſt came to a tower of burniſhed braſs; which upon enquiry they diſco- <pb n="11"/><fw
               rend="align(center)">( 11 )</fw> vered to be kepy by <persName>Clerimond</persName>, ſiſter to <persName>Feragus</persName> and the
            defeated <persName>Green Knight</persName>, and having demanded entrance was reguſed it by the ventinal who guarded the gate, which
            provoked <persName>Valentine</persName> to that degree, that he run againſt him with ſush fury that the centinal fell down dead
            immeadiately.</p>
         <p>The lady <persName>Clerimond</persName> beheld all this dicpute, and ſeeing them brave Knights, recieved them
               courteouſly.—<persName>Valentine</persName> having perſented tokensfrom the <persName>Green Knight</persName> told her, he came there
            fro the love of her, and to diſcourſe with the Allknowing Head, concerning their parents. After dinner, the lady took them by the hand,
            and led them to the chamber of rarieties, where the Head was placed between four pillars of pure jaſper, when, as they entered it made the
            following ſpeech to <persName>Valentine</persName>:</p>
         <p><said>"Thou famous Knight of royal extract <!-- ct ligature --> art called <persName>Valentine</persName> the vlaient, who of right ought
               to marry the lady <persName>Clerimond</persName>. Thou art, ſon to the Emperor of <placeName>Greece</placeName> Empreſs
                  <persName>Belliſant</persName>, who is now in the caſtle of <persName>Feragus</persName>, in <placeName>Portugal</placeName>, where
               they have reſided for twenty years. <persName>King Pepin</persName> is thine uncle, and the <persName>Wild Man</persName> they brother;
               the Empreſs <persName>Belliſant</persName> brought ye two in the freſt of <placeName>Oreleans</placeName>; he was <pb n="12"/><fw
                  rend="align(center)">( 12 )</fw> taken away by a ravenous bear, and thou waſt taken up by thy uncle <persName>Pepin</persName>, who
               brought thee up to man s eſtate <!-- This is weird looking -->. Moreover I likewiſe tell thee, that they brother ſhall never ſpeak till
               thou cutteſt the thread that grows under his tongue.</said></p>
         <p>The <name>Brazen Head</name> having ended his ſpeech, <persName>Valentine</persName> embraced <persName>Orſon</persName> and cut the
            thread which grew under his tongue; and he directly <!-- ct ligature --> related many ſurpriſing things. After which
               <persName>Valnetine</persName> married <persName>Lady Clerimond</persName>, btu not before ſhe turned Chriſtian.</p>
         <p>In the caſtle</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
